Welcome everybody. I'm waiting for my co-chair, who is
probably searching for chairs.
Okay.
Chairs are coming. Yes. So we will start very soon, as soon
as possible, because there are people standing at the back, and I don't want that.
Thank you very much.
Okay, now we have too many.
And the session today is about building resilient data
infrastructures for biodiversity science.
Welcome. Go in, please, as soon as possible.
Okay.
We have a very tight schedule because we have a number of
presenters, and each of us will have 10 minutes.
So 10 minutes of presentation, two minutes for
questions, but of course, after the presentations, we
will have a time for discussion.
So
yes, I think that we already have a full room.
We can start. Giuditta?
Thank you.
Good morning, everyone.
I wanted to briefly introduce myself.
My name is Giuditta Parolini. I work at the
Natural History Museum in Berlin, but it's also the
Leibniz Institute for Evolution and Biodiversity Science.
I am one of your co-organizers of this symposium.
Eva?
The microphone is not on.
Oh,
apologies.
Okay. Okay. So, hi.
My name is Eva Alonso. I'm working at Naturalis Biodiversity Center in
the Netherlands. It's the
National
Science Museum. And yeah, we are the co-chairs.
So let's start introducing the framing a little, the session,
and later we start with the presentations.
Thanks. We first would like to thank all the speakers who
agreed to talk,
to participate in this session, and discuss with us how
data infrastructures in biodiversity science can become more resilient.
Resilience has definitely become an increasingly relevant topic
in research data management in recent years.
The reasons for this are many and very different, and they range
from funding cuts affecting both small and large data
infrastructures to recent technology developments such as
AI clone layers, who are putting research data portals under
pressure, but also political agendas that have caused the
decommissioning of key datasets in environmental and climate
science. It is definitely clear that the risk map for
data and infrastructures in biodiversity science is much more
complex than traditionally envisioned.
Infrastructures must be able to respond promptly and adjust
to changing circumstances if they want to continue serving their
users and fulfilling their mission.
The seven talks in the session cover a multiplicity of
perspectives on the topic of resilience.
There are contributions on specific biodiversity data infrastructures
like GBIF, Bionomia, and Disco, and how they have
addressed resilience, but also discussions of projects
dedicated to rescue environmental data
or make biodiversity data available for a broader group of
stakeholders, including policymakers.
The session also has contributions on general strategies that the
biodiversity community can implement to increase resilience,
such as building an inclusive governance structure, strengthen
communities and narratives around those communities, and
develop data infrastructures that are environmentally sustainable and
therefore require less resources to run.
So resilience
is one of the main components to respond to the risk
of biodiversity data and biodiversity research infrastructures.
And this is a community effort,
so it's nothing that one institution or even one research infrastructure
can do by itself.
When a dataset disappears or a research
infrastructure
turns down, really, the entire community becomes
poorer,
and this is
something that we need really to address as soon as
possible
By now, the committee has been working in standards
and, well, that's why we have this.
Okay, I start becoming a bit nervous with all these doors.
This is
something that we have been working in standards for data
management
and for data policies. And that is why we
have organized this symposium
here
in that week for the enormous effort that that was doing for
many years on that topic. But
right now, we want to call
to the community to start thinking in resilience.
And resilience is not only protecting the data, resilience is protecting
everything, the entire environment around the data management and the
expertise and the tools around that.
So today,
we expect from you contributions
to
start collecting ideas on how research
infrastructures and
national institutions can support resilient
biodiversity data infrastructures and biodiversity
data
in general,
not only from the people here, but also from the people online, because
we have a hybrid session today.
So
let's start with the presentations.
We have here our
schedule, as I said before, is super tight.
In fact, we are already in delay, and we will start with my
presentation about governance.
Okay, no.
Let me check, because that was working very nicely, but not now.
Not any longer.
Okay.
Remote desktop.
Because then we can get the mic.
Jose, no puedo ver las notas. Las veía antes, pero ahora no las puedo
ver
aquí.
Okay.
Yeah.
La presentación ya está.
Vale.
Okay.
So governance is one of the elements we will
present today as one of the elements that really can make
a research infrastructure resilient.
I don't have my notes, so I will need to...
You have to take the mic as well.
Yes.
So
what is governance? What means really governance?
Governance has many definitions.
The organization for economic cooperation,
the OECD,
defines governance and encompasses structural agreements
between its members to achieve objectives beyond simple coordination.
What that means exactly?
Governance set up processes.
Processes to guarantee transparent and fair
operation of research infrastructures or on communities
or institutions, depending on where the governance applies.
Guarantee that the consensus is built through dialogue with the
key actors.
Key actors that for the research infrastructure we are talking here
under that frame
are the scientific communities, not only the communities
of practice of that research infrastructure, but beyond that,
policymakers
and strategic partners. And strategic partners are those who
are
really interested in cooperate and co-create services
and provide services to the users of that specific research
infrastructure.
Governance also include components like the conflict
resolution
mechanisms. But something very important, the governance needs to
be flexible, needs to adapt to the research infrastructure.
It's a mechanism, it's nothing else,
and needs to avoid
administrative overhead.
For a distributed pan-European research infrastructure like the
case of Disco, the example I will bring today here,
we have two levels of governance.
One governance level is the operational one.
We all know it's a typical idea we have when we are talking about
governance,
budget cycle, regulations, the legal form, et
cetera. And this is the mechanics, the interior mechanics of a
research infrastructure to operate.
We need to decide
who decides how and
on what basis, and this is the processes.
But also, and this is a second layer that is, in my opinion, much more
interesting,
is the strategic capability
governance.
What that means?
In a paper that has been published this year
by Gut lever,
he said that research and technical infrastructures are
more than supporting assets to the scientific community.
It's much more than that.
They can be strategic capability systems.
What that means? It means that the research infrastructures and the
collaboration among research infrastructures are
creating systems underpinning
competitiveness,
innovation,
resilience.
So the governance
in that session,
we assume that it's a key component
for that capability generating function
that allows the research infrastructures to
achieve their latest mission, their full potential.
If we understand that governance is a connective tissue,
internally, it's at the background of the entire operation,
from service to innovation, but also externally,
when research infrastructures meet,
we can understand that this connective
tissue is composed by many elements.
I have identified here three, because for me, are the most
important, the three elements that the governance model
has to have to allow the research infrastructure to do what
they need to do.
First, we need to consider an inclusive governance.
Governance needs to be inclusive, needs to, since day one,
understand who are the main key actors.
Second,
governance needs to be a facilitator
to implement scientific outputs
in measures
that can lead to societal benefits,
and also
can be a key component, a key element for research
infrastructures to advocate for less funding
fragmentation and funding bias, which are really
the bread of our days.
Let's go to DiSSCo. This is our case for today.
DiSSCo is a research infrastructure for natural science collections.
Many of us are working in DiSSCo in a way or another.
The ultimate goal is unleash the potential that natural
science collections have for research,
giving access
to the entire collections that we have in our towers, in our museums, in
our
universities, to everybody in a very specific
way, in a fair way.
In that case, we have here
the governance model that DiSSCo will have, because DiSSCo is
not operational yet, will be next year.
And you can see it's a very normal
governance model. Nothing unusual, apparently.
We have
two layers model, the decision-making part, the general assembly,
and the executive part with the director general and the executive board.
And we have advisory bodies, and we have the operational units, the
national infrastructures here.
But
it's in the way the model has been designed
where,
in my opinion, the magic starts.
Let's go.
So
one of these advisory bodies is the Nodes
Advisory Committee.
And this is very important. Why?
Because this Nodes Advisory Committee represents all the nodes
and the service providers, and those
are the key elements of the research infrastructure, the units that
makes real the objectives of the research infrastructure.
At the end, you need to implement it, and it's implemented at national
level.
The importance of the nodes is such for DiSSCo, that it's an advisory
board that advise the director general and also advise
on the direction DiSSCo needs to drive in.
So in principle, it's really having a very real foot
in the execution and in the decision of the research
infrastructure.
And this is part of the status, so it's not something like it's a goodwill,
it's really part of the status, and it's important.
But also inclusiveness
in our model is reflected in the articulating of the status
that recognize
strategic agreements, the possibility
for DiSSCo to write strategic
agreements with third parties.
And what are the third party? Yes. A third party is whoever
institution, agency, international organization that is not
part of DiSSCo, is not paying for DiSSCo in any case,
is not contributing, is not a member, but is super
interested in contributing to the DiSSCo mission.
So as you can see, DiSSCo is trying to
include everybody in this mission.
Second one is the funders and facilities, because keeping funders close
to your heart
really means
that you have long-term sustainability for the research
infrastructure.
And not only that, your agenda aligns
with the national priorities, because you have this communication.
Also, that your national infrastructures are visible,
communicate well, are able to respond to the national needs, and
also benefit from the support and the
protection of the funders at national level.
And this is not granted in every country.
We have many collections that are completely
neglected by our funders.
So having the funders close to our heart has been a long
process, and a slow process as well, at least five years to keep
the funders together with us.
Starting for the Funders Forum, now a non-decision-making
body, so was really unusual, and now having a
decision-making body, the Interim Council.
Interim Council representing more than 18 countries supporting DISCO.
Has been a fantastic vehicle that really
brought a lot of wins. For instance, a lot of success stories
of
nodes
entering the national roadmaps, more than 300
millions of euros
in investment,
but also the communication between our collections and the national funders has
increased enormously. Has nothing to do like we said
before.
Mitigating funding fragmentation is something that is really a problem.
Funding fragmentation deviates our institutions and the research
infrastructures as a whole from its mission, because you are
opportunistic. There is
funding, and you go for that.
We have a case here in the Netherlands.
There are many cases, but I brought the one I am more close by to,
which is in the Netherlands, and it's a coordination mechanism.
15 research infrastructures from the health and the life science
domains sit together and
make a call to the government saying, "Hey,
we have a value.
We are participating in more of the 20 agenda targets of the
country. Recognize that value, sustain that value
financially,
and create a roadmap for us."
This is a good way.
Last slide.
Key messages,
just for you to understand.
Governance is really a connective tissue, internally, but
also externally, allowing research infrastructures to work
together, to govern together
many aspects of their operation. But of course has trade-off,
because you never know
how that works, how long that will endure, and
also how to preserve your uniqueness in that mix.
Funding fragmentation can be mitigated.
There are many cases,
but the challenge is tracing the benefits and the impact in an
evolving complex political context.
Science to policy
is also something that is clear, that can be done.
That is the question of communication with continuous
communication, and not only communication, collaboration with our funders,
but it's also a challenge to keep that interest in a
very short political cycles as well,
and inclusive by design is also a challenge.
Keeping people aware and interested and
engaged in things is always a challenge.
I think.
Probably we don't have any minutes for-- But later, right? Okay.
Oh.
This kind of rolling. If you are able to sit
down.
Okay.
I don't know what I'm saying.
I can sit down, yes. Hello. Come
here.
Go to presentation mode.
Hi.
But can we go to... Okay. Presentation mode.
Control + L.
It's okay. I can do it here.
Sorry. Okay. All
right. As you can see from the title of this presentation, we're going to talk
about the very crucial role
that
engagement or communication and engagement or outreach,
whatever you want to call it, and knowledge or training or skills
capability development
play in contributing, not solving the issue, but in contributing to having a
research infrastructure that is more
resilient, let's say. So we wanted to start by
questioning ourselves, like wonder, okay, what is it that makes
a research infrastructure more resilient against potential pressures?
And there is a little bit of a difference here in kind of mentality that we have to
have, because most of the people here in TAWIC,
when they think about potential pressure, particularly if they have a technical
issue, a technical mind frame, let's say, they will think about data breaches
or
data scrapping or maybe loss of technical
expertise. We have heard before from Judith and from Eva that
threats, pressure, problems can come from a lot of different
origins, let's say. And that's what we're trying to
instill in your minds, let's say. Right?
The kind of
resist and the kind of resilience that you might have in mind is the kind
of resilience that is technical-based or reaction-based.
So if there's a problem, we find a disruption, we need to be able to react to that
disruption. Fine. That's one. Okay?
We're trying to advocate or at least to highlight, from the
communication perspective, a different type of resilience that will be more
based on community and solid
foundations and the preemptive capacity to be ready for when
the crisis comes. So in a way, it's not so much about reacting to something that
happens, but to be solid enough to be able to resist
better whatever happens, let's say.
So-
Following that mind frame, you could say that the definition of what we believe it
is an infrastructure that is resilient is one
that is technically robust, let's say.
Yes, of course. But it's also the one that is used,
that is valuable, and you can demonstrate that value, of course, that is understood
by the community, that is connected and hopefully
interoperable with other initiatives in the sense PACE, and that is relevant for a
sufficiently broad community. This is the definition of what we would say, okay,
it's a resilient infrastructure.
Now,
used, valuable, understood, connected, interoperable, that calls for a double
effort, and we understand that that double effort has to do with communications
engagement and with knowledge and training,
with a caveat.
Both of them have to be, as I say that,
based on user needs. Okay? We say a resilient infrastructure
is one that is relevant for the people, just basically put like that.
But there is no relevance, there is no chance to be relevant unless you serve a
community. So you need to understand their needs, their priorities.
Second, has to be sustained in time. This is not a one-time thing.
You have to continue. I remember Quentin yesterday, no, he's not here, but
Quentin yesterday said, "For some biodiversity decisions,
biodiversity data loses relevance or loses its
usefulness as it grows older," let's say.
And this is something relatively in the same line.
You need to keep it up in a way. All right? Okay.
So
I'm in charge of the communication engagement thing.
Mareike will talk about training and knowledge.
And from the communications perspective, communication engagement, there is a
double loop that kind of works together, and if it works together, complementarily,
I mean,
makes a research infrastructure, in my opinion, more resilient.
The communication loop starts like this.
Yes, you have to try and make visible what you do.
That's important, but sooner rather than later, you have to turn that visibility
into understanding by talking. Please, have in mind that I'm a
communications person. I didn't introduce myself, by the way, Mareike.
Anyway, I'm a communication officer, okay?
I'm not technical. So don't ask technical questions.
Anyway,
the visibility needs to transform really easily or really fast
into understanding. That is, why what we do matters, or why what we do is
important.
Only if you do that,
people will get closer to you and will want to learn about what you
do and will want to do what you offer them to do.
We will talk about this later with Mareike. Okay?
But the thing is that obviously communication can support this area, too.
Now, this is something that some people say, "Okay, people use my research
infrastructure. We're done." No, you're not done. Why?
Because you have to demonstrate the value of what you do, of what you offer.
In other words, you have to report the impact.
People will use it, and people will get some results out of it, let's say.
It's very important that you report on the impact, because only if a community can
see what you do, can see why it matters, and can see that it actually
works,
will support you. And if you have a community behind you supporting you,
you become more resilient. This is at least the theory that I want to transmit
to you. We saw an example yesterday in BHL,
when we were talking about the problems that they had and everything.
You saw a very beautiful example at the end with all these tweets and all these
messages from the people.
That might be part of why they're resilient or why they're managing to
survive, let's say.
Communication loop. The engagement loop is something a little different because the
communication loop is something you do on your own, let's say, but for this one,
you need other people.
What the communication people can do here is that they can initiate the
dialogue
with other initiatives in the same space, with other infrastructures.
That dialogue has to be necessarily about what we need, how we fit each other, that
kind of thing. We can support that, so we end up
getting some technical alignment, technical interoperability.
Communication people don't have anything to do in there. That's a technical thing.
But if it happens, it can happen with the support of communications.
Now,
this is where the magic happens, because five minutes to go. Okay.
One more minute, and I'll give it to you.
If there happens the alignment, interoperability,
your research infrastructure expands into a new ecosystem.
Why? Because you will have your data, you will have your services, and they will
have their primary value, but it might actually be relevant for other people, too,
the other people in the other initiatives. So you get additional value to that.
If you get more relevance for a wider community, that means that more people will
want that you survive in a way. So you get resilience to there.
Now,
double loop, as I said, the communication loop ensures,
contributes to get community support.
The engagement loop contributes to get expanded relevance.
Both of them working together from the side of the communications engagement means
a little bit more resilience. You're invading my space right now.
Here we go.
Thank you.
So I just would like to add on that the more or less
knowledge and training part. So I can just briefly
introduce us, because I was leading the outreach and
communication subcommittee in TEDRIC, so together-
Oh, similarly
... and he was member of that, so that's the reason we are giving this
presentation here today. And Deb as well. Yeah. Thank you. Yeah.
And I think when it's coming to
training, I think it's really important.
It's an addition to engagement with our
community. And if you think one of our biggest
infrastructure
are our natural science research infrastructures.
And of course, a textbook or an online documentation might
be not sufficient. So we need really a user-centered
training portfolio which is adapted to the user needs.
So as a research infrastructure, the first question we need to ask
ourselves is what Eva and Jose already mentioned,
is our user community. Who are actually the users?
What are we
developing our infrastructure for, and how would they
like to be trained? So is it a one-week workshop where they
spend all their time for training in this direction, or is it
maybe a scattered workshop, one
hour this week, another hour the other week?
So this needs to be tackled. Then
you have different skill sets which you would like to transport, to
disseminate. And of course, for some courses, you can have
self-learning online courses that people can sit by themselves
and get trained with their computer.
But other skills you would like to disseminate, they require workshops, they
require interaction between the trainer and the attendees, but of course,
also among the peers.
And
it's your research infrastructure, and you have maybe particular training which
is really linked to that infrastructure, and others which can be disseminated
by other parties. For example, I don't think that Disco needs
to cover introduction into research data management, or Tetrik also
doesn't need to cover that, because there are a lot of other parties
where users can get those kind of information.
What I would like to bring to the table here is that, of
course, we all did a lot of training, Tetrik, GBIF, IDIC Bio,
a lot. But this was really mostly either for those
people developing the infrastructure, so collection
managers, data managers, data architect, whatever,
how you name them, who are growing with our infrastructures,
or for a particular use case. For example, there's a new
package, a new application available, and there's a documentation, maybe
a workshop, and then it's done.
But I would like to add one additional point, to see
also
training and knowledge with the angle of a
sustainable infrastructure, because I think this is what we need.
So we need an engagement with our community, but we also
need continuously trained users of our community, because
otherwise it's just an empty
space and nobody will use that anymore.
And as we already mentioned, infrastructures are changing over time, so this
needs to be continuously adapted.
And we are investing a lot of money, personal staff in
building infrastructures, and I think we also should invest a
lot into our end users to make use of them.
So it's a kind of reinvestment that in the end, what is, I
think, required.
And with this,
I think I would like to sum up our
presentation, and we are of course open for discussion afterwards because we're
communication people.
So first of all, I think that's not just for the technical
infrastructure, it's also how to engage with your community, know your
users and their needs. So what is really required?
And invest in the sustained effort, and not just in a technical
manner, not just in your
server infrastructure, also in the people.
And make visible what you have, but also the why.
Why should they use that? How to engage with them?
Have incentives. What makes their research better if they're using
this kind of infrastructure? And deliver, of course, training for
that. And report impact, I think that's also
important. Also,
if you're engaging with your community, what does it change?
How does it change the way you are working and thinking?
And of course, engage with others so we are not alone
on Earth. So engage with other infrastructures and learn from each other.
And, I think the last one, adapt your training to your users, was already
mentioned. So with this, thank you.
Would you like to add a last sentence?
No.
Okay, then. Thank you.
Thanks.
The topic of my talk is the role that environmental
sustainability can have as a strategy to build more
resilient data infrastructures in biodiversity science.
This talk emerges at the confluence of two sets
of consideration. The first set of consideration is
related to my current research, that is about sustainability in
research data management in biodiversity science.
I guess that many of you already heard about sustainability in this
context, but I think that in many cases,
you heard about it in relation to financial aspects.
In some cases, maybe also in relation to social aspects.
For instance, the
considerations about traditional knowledge and the role of data
that was part of one of the keynotes.
But I think that you-
Basically never heard it in relation to environmental aspects.
And yet, this is definitely something that should be
taken into account because research data management uses
IT infrastructures, and these IT infrastructures are
resource-intensive, and the environmental impact of these
infrastructures is also constantly increasing because we
have more and more data to manage, and also we are offering more and
more services to our users. And this means increased
electricity use and therefore increased greenhouse gas emissions.
Means also that we need more resources to produce hardware.
And in the end, this also means that we will have more e-waste
because we are now very bad at recycling electronic
equipment. The list could continue, but I think that this
gives an idea of why it is important to consider these
aspects. The second set of considerations
that are behind this talk are related to the fact that
we live in challenging times, and we cannot and should
not take for granted the unconditional availability of
key resources, energy, for instance, when we develop research
infrastructures. This is, of course, not my opinion.
It is what emerges from the reports of
policymakers. For instance, the most recent report of
the International Energy Agency, that is the organization that
survey worldwide the
energy situation. It is that there are three
critical aspects, at least three main critical aspects.
The first one is that energy demand is growing, but
the increasing geopolitical fragmentation and fragility makes
difficult to supply this energy that is required.
And
even if there were not this fragmentation, there
would still be problems because distribution
grids are not growing as fast as the requirements
that we have about energy. One key case, for instance, is
the sudden growth of the data center industry, driven by
the generative AI industry. And this is
definitely putting under pressure the electric grids
in many countries and not just in a few ones.
But this is just one of the weaknesses.
The other one important that is underlined and stressed
by the International Energy Agency is that
the supply chains of key materials are now under
pressures.
You may have heard that in 2025, China imposed an
export ban on rare earth elements, and these are key
in order to produce electronic equipment.
The European Union was not particularly pleased about it, and
I think that everyone has a sense of how much the prices
of electronic equipment have been rising in
recent times, and what this means practically when you need
this. But this is not the only problem.
There are also problem in provisioning, for instance, lithium for
producing batteries. So it is a whole lot of
things that comes together. And last but not least, the
International Energy Agency points out that
intervention to reduce global carbon emission and to
mitigate climate change and the risks that are
associated to climate change are not progressing
as much as expected. And this means in the end that we have
more risks to manage. And this is
why
resilience come into being. In my talk,
resilience in relation to research infrastructures
means the continued availability of the core services
in the face of political, legal, financial, and technological
changes. You may add more categories, but I think that these
four already make quite a good starting point.
And how do you build resilience? First of all, you need to decide
what are your core services, so what you want to protect.
Then you need to understand what are the risks
that
are a menace for your core services.
And then in the end, you need to have a risk management strategy.
And here comes the environmental considerations.
In 2023, the European Strategy Forum on Research
Infrastructures wrote a report on energy and
supply challenges of research infrastructures.
This report was written in the wake of the COVID pandemic
and of the Russian invasion of Ukraine that created so
much concern in Europe about the provisioning of gas in the
winter 2022-2023.
And the key recommendations that ESFRI
made for both national policymakers and research
infrastructures were to green operations, where greening operation doesn't
mean just consume less energy, but also think about
the materials that you need, especially the one that are rare and not
available on the market. Think about reusing and
recycling.
And the
reason for this is not because the
European Strategy Forum is staffed by convinced environmentalist, I
would say. The point is that they are policy advisors, and
as policy advisors, they see all the risks that are coming up,
and how thinking in terms of environmental sustainability
is simply a risk management strategy.
If you have a frugal infrastructure, this infrastructure is going to face
less risks when hardware is going to cost 10 times
more than it used to cost
a few years ago because
These are problems. The price of energy has also increased.
These are all aspects that should be taken into consideration.
And in the case of biodiversity data infrastructures, this point
should be very clear because biodiversity data are data especially
at risks. Because these are not just data for
scientists, they are data for policymakers.
In the European Union, where there is this concept of sustainable
financing, they are also important data for the financial
advisors. They are data with
a sort of political interest, as has been seen in
recent years, especially in relation to aspects like
environmental protection and climate.
So they are really data that can be contentious, and
these should be kept in mind. And of course, they also
face very material risks like energy prices
increasing,
unavailability of hardware or increasing costs for hardware.
But in the European Union, for instance, there are increasing environmental
regulations and there are also increasing reporting duties.
And this also puts further risks that are compliance and reporting
risks. And so this is when it comes into
being the value of environmental sustainability as a
risk management strategy. The recommendation that the
European Strategy Forum made in 2023 should be even
more heard by the managers of biodiversity data
infrastructures today in 2026, because it
is clear that the infrastructures that really keep
environmental sustainability in mind and so need less resources
are better placed to face the risks that are increasing.
And this is the reason why when I talk about these
aspects, people tell me, "Oh, environmental sustainability is a nice-to-have." No,
this is not the point. It's not a nice-to-have.
Even though you may not be particularly concerned personally
about this point, this is really a risk management strategy
because you need to keep these risks in mind,
and you need to have a strategy to face them.
And these risks are coming true. We see it every
day. So my take-home message is that you really need
to build the data infrastructure in biodiversity science with environmental
sustainability in mind if you want to make them more
resilient in the time of crisis that we are living in.
Thanks.
Yeah. Okay. Let's see.
But there's somebody who maybe you have a chance.
Good morning, everyone. I'm Rachel Blake. I'm with Intertidal Agency.
We are a nonprofit based in the US working on data
governance and data stewardship, and I'll be sharing some of this work of
my colleagues and a whole bunch of other data professionals with you
today.
I'm sure those of you joining us this morning understand and have
probably experienced the increasing demand for high-quality data
of all kinds, but especially for nature, environmental, and
biodiversity data. And this is for many reasons, such
as to solve large-scale problems, to answer important
questions, to enable cross-domain analyses
and data products, and of course, to support AI readiness.
In early 2025, it became apparent to
much of the scientific community, especially in the US, that the
community and society overall really risked losing
not only data and publications, but entire archives and
repositories of high-quality data.
In some cases, fragile systems had been kept running with
patches for many years,
but the sudden changes
in personnel and funding
really exposed that fragility and things did break and
things were lost.
A few examples include the Environmental Justice and
Screening Tool, EJSCREEN, which was hosted by the
US Environmental Protection Agency, and now is
unofficially hosted by Public Environmental Data Partners.
Another example is the US billion-dollar Weather and Climate
Disasters database, which was hosted by the National
Oceanographic and Atmospheric Administration in the US
and is now hosted at Climate Central with the same lead scientist.
And finally,
the Socioeconomic Data and Applications Center
was at Columbia University,
and it hosted multiple scales of data about urban
environments and sustainable development goals.
And that was shut down, and the data has been archived at
NASA and the Harvard Dataverse repository.
So those are just a few examples of some things that were broken
or lost.
But what was
most surprising about these disruptions and crises
was the fragility
that they revealed because of the speed and magnitude of these changes.
But the need to preserve data wasn't new.
The Environmental Data Governance Initiative worked about 10 years
ago on a lot of data rescue efforts,
and
This time was a little bit different, though, because there was a lot more
awareness among non-data experts about the
risks to data
and concerns for rescuing that data.
There are also threats around the globe to data from not just
societal change, but wildfires, tsunamis, and earthquakes, and cyber
attacks, and
service disruptions.
So in 2025, a lot of the immediate response to these
disruptions was panic among data professionals, among experts,
among non-experts
alike. And many copies of data were made
by all of those groups of people
because everyone wanted to feel like they were rescuing data.
The public environmental data partners and other rescue efforts
reactivated or started up,
and they tried to manage this onslaught of volunteers who really
wanted to help out,
as well as the myriad of tips that came in about data that were
perceived or actually were at risk of going away.
But a lot of this panic copying, especially without understanding
the context or copying the metadata along with it,
really led to more fragmentation and data without that
context and
important information that goes along with the data.
And this really did not support long-term interoperability and
reusability of the data.
But there were copies made by those who saved the metadata,
who understood the data, and were able to reconstruct some of these
data sets and data services and
projects. And so the short-term recovery for some of these
sources of information
was focused on making these data available again.
Some of the common approaches to doing this included putting data up on
domain-specific repositories
and putting data on generalist repositories. A lot of data went to Zenodo.
That was a common solution for where do we put this data we just rescued.
And another approach was to stand up bespoke tech architecture
for hosting websites or data products or data explorer tools.
An example is the Environmental Protection Agency Risk Management Plan
database,
which
was too big and unwieldy to put on Zenodo and so is now being
served through Datasette as a searchable SQLite
database. Billion-Dollar Disasters data set, which I just mentioned, went to a
new host organization. The
EJSCREEN tool went up on a new website hosted by a
new organization, and some work that I've been involved with
at Intertidal,
protecting data and information on US
endangered and protected species is being archived on
Zenodo as well.
There's also work going on towards building better and more
resilient systems, and a few of those examples
include working towards
building tools that assess resilience, such as the repository
crisis scorecards.
And this is a tool for a self-assessment by a repository
staff for the resilience of that repository.
There are also groups working to support people and the resilience of
people to some of these disruptions and crises.
And one group doing that is the Climate Reserve at the Aspen Global Change
Institute, which is funding work
by former US federal government workers to continue doing the good work that
they do with data. And there are also groups that are
gathering together to support the technical infrastructure and making
that more resilient, one of those being the Council of Data Facilities,
that is looking at sharing and replication
across technical infrastructures.
So these crises and disruptions also provided the
catalyst for some larger scale sort of
redesign, proactive planning
efforts,
thinking about future data systems and how do we build those.
So the community is and has been moving from this
immediate data copying to the long-term system
design and development.
In other words, the old system was broken.
How do we design and build a new system so that it is better than what we had
before?
So a few of the needs that have repeatedly come up are the need to
preserve expertise, institutional knowledge, and operational
capacity. And then another important need is for data to be useful
and fit for purpose.
So how do we address these needs and design a more resilient data
system for the long term?
I'm going to argue that we need to invest in human infrastructure,
interoperability,
distributed federated networks, which I'm not going to talk about today, but others
are working on this aspect as well, and purpose-driven data
products.
So I'll quickly highlight a few organizations working on
some of these efforts. One is the Coalition for Resilient Research Data
Infrastructure,
and their guiding principles are to assess and monitor the
repository landscape, to develop diverse, sustained
funding and governance, and to build a shared outreach, advocacy,
and action strategy.
Another effort is the American Geophysical Union's Global Data Convening,
and they seek to establish a global collaborative network
for data and research data. They want to
finalize best practices for dataset threat mitigation and
create a roadmap to secure a sustainable, resilient data future.
So these are complementary efforts,
and there are some more targeted efforts, which I will just
highlight here. One being the Semantic Commons for Climate,
Nature, and Economy. And their guiding principles are to
have data be interoperable and models be
interoperable across domains to preserve expertise and
capture that expertise in a machine-readable way.
But they've encountered some challenges, such as heterogeneous data,
especially when you're working across domains, and domain-specific jargon.
Another example is the World Ocean Database.
This is a large assemblage of data from many sources
that are used for many different purposes around the globe.
And the goal of this work, so this database has existed for a while, but this
new effort is to ensure the resilience and sustainability of this
database. And they're working to standardize and document the data as
close to collection as possible and to make the data more
interoperable. But some of the challenges they're encountering is that it's a
really small team, and that team has been reduced in the past year and a half.
And they're interacting with 92 countries,
and have to interpret heterogeneous data from many sources.
Proactive planning for the future also includes training the next generation of
data stewards and there are many efforts out there doing this.
One is the effort that we have on ocean data stewardship
training. It's a program that we launched this year, and there are a couple other
complementary
programs up here on the slides. But I want to leave you with a few
final thoughts, because we can't rely only on technical
solutions to make data more robust and resilient and
make our data systems more robust and resilient.
We have to preserve human expertise, institutional knowledge, and operation
capacity. But we also must invest in the complicated and
messy maintenance,
coordination, and translation that's really key to durable infrastructure.
And finally, we have to prioritize interoperability
and standardize and document data as close to collection as possible.
So I ran through a lot of information.
There are references and links at that
URL at the top there. And if you like nudibranchs or you want to talk more about
this stuff, come find me later. I have stickers. Thank you.
That was the easiest way.
Okay. Where do I find these presentations here? Somewhere here?
Folder?
What? Good
question.
Should it help?
Yes.
Oh.
Just to close it?
This one.
Yeah.
Close?
Yes, sir.
Here?
Just close this one.
Okay.
Folder.
No, I'm closing that one. Yeah, close all tabs.
Close all.
And here.
You can find them now in your presentation.
Okay.
And then control and then it will be there on your screen.
It doesn't fire up. Sorry.
Control.
Yeah. It's not a PDF, no? It's a PowerPoint presentation.
Oh, okay.
I have to use Windows. This one here?
Yeah.
Okay.
So now I have to switch the...
Eins, zwei, Polizei. Okay, cool. Thanks.
Thanks for having me here. My name is Klaus Wallen from Senckenberg.
I will present today a approach we call Pixel to Policy,
to make data rescue ready. We, this are essentially Aydin Yumur
and his team and my team at Senckenberg.
Aydin is from our science policy unit.
I'm leading the collection management team.
My other co-authors are providing actual use cases for this.
I will go into their role deeper in course of the talk.
So as we already have heard, global research data is at risk
on a global scale. We have institutional defunding. We heard about this.
This goes hand in hand, of course, with strategic reprioritizations.
We see more money going away from earth and environmental
observations into
homeland defense, homeland security, and a general pivot for
AI.
And in addition to these two
already ongoing processes, we see that there is conflict and structural loss.
Those are
digital infrastructures, and the digital assets are themselves under
threat due to armed conflicts.
However, we are essentially dependent on this global
interconnected network of deployed sensors and other
data-capturing infrastructures, so we need some kind of
mitigation approach to ensure long-term data resilience for these
infrastructures. And one approach was already mentioned,
AGAU's international efforts to develop a global
data rescue framework,
within the context or framework of the American
Geophysical Union.
Several German key players in earth and environmental
sciences set up a project to secure endangered data
called
SEND, Secure Endangered Earth Data, backed up by German national
funding, the DFG. And the core objective in our SEND Earth Data
project is to deliver preservation workflows in addition or embedded
in legal guidance, so to deploy this also with correct data usage
agreements. We want to build resilient hardware infrastructure to this,
so storage is, of course, an aim. We all- Spoke about this.
And on top of this, above the technical stuff, we want to establish
a national data sovereignty network.
And this will be grounded in an already existing research data
infrastructure, the NFDI for Earth System Sciences.
And this approach will, as I've already said, be fully embedded in the
Global Data Resilience Framework, spearheaded by AGU.
So we started two months ago with Earth data.
There are already first implementations by our team at
Senckenberg. I go quickly over these use cases.
We want to harmonize and integrate endangered camera trap data we get
from
Polissya in the Ukraine. We do this in collaboration with our
partners, the Frankfurt Zoological Society, who operates already several
years in this region. This is in particular
this area here.
We want to employ a digital object approach for multidisciplinary
data, combining socio-ecological data and
collected biodiversity monitoring data from several sites in
Yemen, in particular from the Socotra Island.
We're also doing this for a couple of years and now improve the technical
infrastructure and make it rescue-ready with our partner,
the Royal Society for the Conservation of Nature in Jordan, who
leads the UNEP and GEF mission there in Yemen.
And we want, as I already said, establish redundant cloud
storage, in particular for animal tracking data.
We do this also with our already established community infrastructure,
Movebank, hosted by the Max Planck Institute for Animal Behavior.
So how do we want to achieve this rescue-ready
artifact aggregation? I will detail this on the example of the
camera trap data we do in the context of AI for wildlife.
Very similar approaches can be applied to the material sample and
specimen data. I will touch this a little bit, but when we look at
such a digitization and data capturing process, we see it
with the image capture. We can do a lot of these images.
We can obtain annotations from it with machine learning, where we do
taxonomic determination or measure quantitative traits of
it. And all these annotations, in addition to other
derived data products,
can be collected. If we have a material sample from the same place, we can draw
DNA from it. We can, of course, link the geolocation to Earth
observation time series, for example, the deforestation of the
place where this animal was observed here in the Chiquitano dry forest in
Bolivia.
We can link it to policies which can be themselves machine interpretable, in
this case, an import prohibition for that particular species.
And we can capture all these computational steps in a kind of acyclic
graph. We call this workflow verification here and
relate it to that as well. We can put licenses on all
items appearing in this process. So the idea is, how do we
make this transient network into something which we can easily
rescue and redeploy? And what we're actually doing is we're drawing
a box around that whole thing in software.
And in the process of building this box, we attach
essentially two additional artifacts on it.
One is an identificator to make the thing resolvable and findable
on the internet. And the other thing is we give that thing a name, which is
somewhat cryptic here, capture event, because we call this a capture event
FDO type. We call that whole thing, the whole box, a fair digital
object. And fair digital object is, so to say, is the
objectification of this relational network in cyberspace.
There are several ways to implement these fair digital objects.
This is by no means a new idea. Many people are working on this,
and you have probably or certainly heard several names for this.
We built the fair digital object. We do
completely on a web technology stack, so we use
schema.org to build this box around.
We use a standard, our crate, it's just a name,
to build this box. We use other standard formats like Bio
Schemas to represent the items inside.
We use MLFC Croissant to decorate this box
with IR ready directives, so the box can be used by
machine learning framework and so on.
And since we use this web technology step, we call the whole thing
WebFDO.
But there are different implementations for this.
You have certainly heard of the digital specimen in Disco.
That's essentially the same concept on a high level.
So how do we want to achieve the semantic interoperability?
I will touch this a bit more. We want to focus and
build on a minimal high-impact core of established formats.
I already mentioned the JSON LD derived schema.org
schema, and supplement this with pluggable semantic
ontologies for the domain content wherever possible.
Stay with the upper semantic artifacts, but then go a bit more down where we need
detail. For example, for the capture event, which has essentially two
components,
the image capturing, which can be a burst triggered by the animal
passing by, and the annotation put and on so on.
We developed this wildlife monitoring ontology, which provides us a
capture event,
which is the core of the digital object, and we link it also to Earth
observation data, which is a station setup.
And this WLMO itself derives then from a standard
ontology called Sosa. So we try to be
as community related as possible.
Of course, mappings are involved in all sorts of the process.
We have to export that thing with standards to standard mapping our own
standards, WLMO to CamtrapDP, for example.
For upload of camtrap data here we use a standard for canonical mapping called
Simple Standard for Mapping Ontologies, SSMO.
So I will use the last minute to go a little bit deeper how we want to preserve the
policy part.
We want to embed machine interpretable policy objects directly in
the rescue kit.
We do this with
other additional format called Open Digital Rights Language, which delivers us the
policy types here, an ODL permission
to preserve the policy. We then want to link it, of course, to legal context, which
help we preserve. We use a
European legal identifier ontology for this.
We can do this, of course, only within the framework of the EU.
This is from a project called Biodiversity Meets Data.
You heard yesterday of
which is used then to migrate this data and redeploy it by preserving
the reference to the original
directive, in this case, a nature restoration law.
And we would send that to the most interesting part, probably,
add data pipelines to it in a machine interpretable way,
in this case, an ODL duty report back to an agent
in case you do something with the original data, for example, update an
indicator and so on. So this is our idea
to preserve the policy and the data pipelines linked to the policy within the
migration process.
Summarizing what I have showed, I gave at least an overview of how
we want to foster rescue and readiness by
leveraging a set of community specifications, supplemented
by pluggable domain ontologies, including, for example,
WLMO or Open DS for specimen data. We want to
utilize these then packaged in containers, WebSDO as
data lifeboats to provide resilient
data failovers and let these
data lifeboats float into uptaking infrastructures.
And of course, the technological part is never sufficient alone.
We want to establish a multi-tier resiliency network starting
from the national level, some due to funding in the framework of German
NFDI, for example,
or parallel European initiatives, going to European scale
in the framework of the research infrastructures like Disco or
in the context of the common European data spaces like EOSC, which
is Earth and Environmental Node Data Terra, going towards
this global data resilience framework envisioned by AGU.
Many thanks.
I have some notes because I have some quotes from the slides for later.
I'm Matthew Blissett. I'm a software developer at GBIF.
I'm responsible for resilience of our infrastructure,
reliability, keeping it all working, and some other things too.
This is a bit more technical, I think, than some of the previous ones.
We are an existing resilient, I think, infrastructure.
But times have changed, and since about
two years ago,
two to three years ago,
the pattern of usage has changed significantly.
So first, a bit of history.
In the early 2000s, Chadwick introduced standards for data sharing,
Digger, Taper, later Biocase works in a similar way.
It was intended that a request to GBIF to search for something would then
fan out to a few hundred data publishers,
give them the same request, and we'd aggregate the little bits of
responses
and send you the results.
That proved unreliable. It couldn't cope
with
hundreds of different publishers. Sometimes one would be offline.
So from 2007, GBIF built a central occurrence
index.
That meant
GBIF retrieving all of the data from all of the publishers.
And that meant making thousands of requests to each of the publishers,
paging through all these XML-based protocols like you see,
to retrieve every single record.
That meant GBIF overwhelming the publishers.
So to avoid that, we had a distributed locking system.
Our system would only make a single request at any point
to a particular server.
Nowadays, almost everything, I think actually everything now is
using Darwin Core Archives or Darwin Core data packages or camera trap
packages.
So these solve the problem. There's only a single request to
download a zip file, which is already generated. It's quite easy.
So we check every week.
We respect the HTTP not modified responses.
If nothing's changed, we don't do anything.
The other place we get data from publishers is the image caching.
If you open an image page on the GBIF website, you get
50 images, and you can keep scrolling down to get more and more.
That's quite a significant load on the publishers because there can be
thousands of the same
publisher's images on one page. So we cache them for at least a
year.
But beginning
sometime this year, early spring or so, we started to find
publishers being overwhelmed, not just by the
requests coming via GBIF services, but by
probably AI LLM training people
directly requesting the images because they're also public
URLs.
This has been serious, significant problems for quite a few publishers.
It's not quite a problem for GBIF's own servers, but
it's close.
We see hundreds of simultaneous connections
This behavior of the LLM services is totally
different to anything we've seen before.
People, instead of using one or two connections to slowly get what they need,
they make 3,000 connections
and go as fast as they possibly can.
So we're going to need to introduce the same kind of thing, making sure
we limit what we retrieve from the publisher.
We can't really help the publisher.
They'll each need to implement their own limits,
at least if the URLs are public, which is the whole point of sharing them
with GBIF.
This is a chart of the usage of GBIF's
website coming through search engines.
As you can see, the peak is around
early 2025.
These are the well-known search engines, Google, Bing, Baidu, and so on.
They respect the robots.txt file. That's a file published on the website.
It tells you, for example,
don't go downloading every individual occurrence page.
Don't do all the searches.
But you can look at the data sets. You can look at the downloads.
You can look at the taxon pages.
These are easy to manage. We introduced some stronger rate limiting just
after the peak, and then even stronger rate limiting at the end
of 2025.
But each of these services are identifiable.
It's straightforward to just tell them, "Slow down.
You can only retrieve two or three pages a second," say.
I can't remember the limit.
You can see that the same peak is why we had to introduce rate limiting
here. This is what the LLM training ones, the major
providers that do identify themselves. So that's the traffic they brought us.
Some of them do respect the robots.txt the same way as the search engines.
They're also easy to rate limit or to block.
Some of them,
rhymes with Facebook,
they don't respect it. They completely ignore it.
So they just got blocked completely.
It's not worth our time to
try and deal with someone who
isn't being polite.
But yeah, it's a similar thing that's also manageable to deal
with that.
Once those LLMs have been trained, people start using them.
This is a
slightly different scale on the graph, but I think
that's half the height.
For a very long time, and you see on the left of the graph, there
were
websites like Global Biotic Interactions, for example,
making a few requests to GBIF. Also, many museum websites that had a little
embedding of something in our API.
It barely registers on the graph, that kind of use.
Since
March 2025, oops, didn't mean...
New things came with strange names that you haven't heard of.
Bird.world is the green one. BioTag is the blue one.
They look like they're vibe-coded apps using
these services. They make
incredibly inefficient use of the GBIF API.
I think one of them is about six million requests each day for
data that could be a single download, and they'd have it in 15 minutes.
You try and rate limit them, they don't really care.
They just leave it running forever.
They're online for a little bit, then they disappear.
I think they're probably people, students,
whoever, developers experimenting with a reasonably
popular open API.
The result is things like this. This is Bird.world.
This is a German houseplant website.
This is an American one about growing plants.
This is British
nature reserves and things. This is Japanese. It's the same.
This is somewhere else, nature guide.
Social science one. This is different.
There's over
100 of these that make over 100,000 requests to GBIF in the
last few months.
So where does that come from? The traffic's been increasing.
And it seems like it comes from these residential proxy crawlers.
You have a smart TV at home, your child perhaps, or you.
You install this game. It says, "To enjoy this game without ads, please allow web
indexing by Bright Data to occasionally use your device's free resources
to download public web data." You just press Agree.
In the tiny text, which you probably can't read, Bright Data runs in the background
even after closing this application.
So if you install a smart TV game or a free football
watching thing,
you're part of this proxy network.
The text on the left says, "Experience
seamless scraping with the industry's fastest residential proxies.
400 million ethical residential IPs."
So the new crawling that is really difficult to block,
we get one or two requests from an IP address. That's it for the month.
How do we identify that? They pretend to be a web browser.
It's really difficult.
There's commercial services.
Oops, just got to wait, but I won't wait.
So we introduced Cloudflare.
It's a little bit disappointing. It doesn't actually block more than half of these
things.
So instead, we've had to change the
web pages, have less information on them, make them simpler,
put some of the information, instead of it being up to the second up to
date, it's cached. It's updated once a day.
And to some extent, we're trying to categorize these requests to try and work out
what we can deny
The search engines, for example, if there's a high load, we can say to search
engines, "You're blocked for the moment.
Come back later."
The future plan is basically continue to do that.
It's more development time that we didn't really want to spend, but there we go.
Pre-calculating more data, trying to find these patterns.
We're trying to extend the monthly cloud uploads to put more data in.
Some of the LLMs seem maybe to be using them,
but so far, most of them are not.
We really don't want to introduce API keys because
it's an open API, and people appreciate that.
I think that's all I have.
Is it-
I'm really conscious there's a lot of people outside-
Oh, yeah
... who want to come in.
Everyone come in.
A little effort to
maybe get some more people to fray on the floor.
I think it might be a good
thing.
It's a video next, right?
Yeah.
We just play it?
I don't know.
I thought that it was of the organization to play the video.
Sorry.
Thank you, Judita and Eva, for the invitation to present in your session
on building resilient data infrastructures for biodiversity science.
I am the maintainer of Bionomia, which combines automation and
volunteerism to facilitate the creation and maintenance of
more than 50 million attributable connections between biodiversity
records and human expertise. Its interface has been
translated into seven languages through the generous efforts of
linguists on Crowdin.
Bionomia receives modest daily human traffic with
occasional hourly spikes in the tens of thousands of people and is
generally manageable with a cloud-based technical
infrastructure across root-level access to three
adequately provisioned virtual machines on DigitalOcean for
database asset resizing and caching and search or
programmatic API usage, as well as a job queue on
Redis to orchestrate long-running tasks.
However, Bionomia has faced challenges from multiple sources,
including many you see here. Some, like code maintenance
and server upkeep, have well-known solutions.
Others, like institutional oversight, for instance,
raise persistent questions about its relationship with my
employer, particularly when there are spikes in its
international visibility.
More recently, misbehaving bots and AI crawlers
have significantly degraded performance, taking down the website
on dozens of occasions.
Mercifully, Cloudflare now acts as a gatekeeper
to thwart most of these AI crawlers, and I can quickly
adjust fine-grained new actions, such as blocking whole
countries from access, while I develop more appropriate solutions
to stymie bad actors.
But I worry about the long-term sustainability of Cloudflare itself
and its relationship with a global
web community.
In addition to RESTful API and reconciliation
endpoints that do not participate in these Cloudflare
filters,
the code base is made more resilient through the encapsulation
of core functions into high-performant standalone libraries
of code, such as a RubyGem, now ported into
Go for the parsing of human names, as is typically
expressed in Darwin Core terms.
Once a month, a graph structure in CSV form is
produced and then zipped up and pushed into Zenodo, an
industry-standard archive.
In theory, one could build a triplestore from this structure, and I welcome
those who may wish to do so.
Likewise, Bionomia auto-archives a CSV-based
frictionless data package to Zenodo every month for each of
the roughly 9,000 data sets that share their data to GBIF.
Each package contains unique lists of people identified
by their ORCID or Wikidata Q numbers, relationally
linked to one-to-many occurrence records to express whether they collected
or identified those specimens, as well as files that
identify logically incongruent records, such as those
whose values for collection date fall
before a collector's date of birth or after their death.
Volunteer scribes, as they're called in Bionomia, create and
maintain these links between GBIF occurrence records and
those industry-recognized expressions of identity for
collectors and determiners as either ORCID IDs or
Wikidata Q numbers. The expectation is that data
providers to GBIF, like herbaria and museums, may,
at their leisure, examine and incorporate these new
data enhancements into their local stores, thus completing a
data round trip, and many now do.
For instance, staff at the Natural History Museum at the University of
Oslo use these frictionless data packages to fill new
gaps as they digitize new records, then share the
Wikidata and ORCID identifiers directly to GBIF in
purpose-built Darwin Core terms.
Individual researchers also participate in archiving their
occurrence records, as shown on GBIF, through integration between
Bionomia and Zenodo. Here, Sabina has a data site
DOI, you can see at the bottom left on this figure in a badge,
and a formatted citation, and she puts these into her curriculum
vitae.
In summary, relatively small niche projects may
be resilient in the short term within a landscape of
large-scale, well-funded biodiversity infrastructure if they
acknowledge and plan for decommissioning at the outset.
That perspective results in laser focus on
simplicity for the data schema, the website code,
search algorithms, and when to say no to new features.
Counterintuitively, it also means finding ways to eliminate any
technical debt others may incur by using the
products of what may be a short-lived project.
Reusable libraries of code in multiple programming languages
and distributed and versioned data archives in multiple forms
help reduce that technical debt and, in turn,
actually create more generous, welcoming environments
in which to work.
I am grateful to the volunteers in Bionomia who have each carved
out a vision of their own, the translators who have helped create a more
universally accessible environment, the Biological Collections in
Ecology and Evolution network for their support, and to
Andrea, Sean, and Tonell, whose leadership has resulted
in well-attended workshops throughout botany meetings in the United States,
and to many others who have offered their time and energies and have
added their voices and perspectives to Bionomia's
mission. Thank you very much.
Thank you, Judita and Eva, for the invitation to present in your session
on building resilient data infrastructures for biodiversity science.
Okay, so now it's time for discussion.
I really would like to invite the speakers here, if it's possible,
for the round of questions from the audience and also
from the chat. I think Judita will
have a look at this.
So a lot of information I can understand,
and a lot of different information, different approaches.
So just feel free to raise your hand and
make a question or just contribute to the discussion.
Sorry, before starting, I just would like to make two announcements.
The first one is that
today in the afternoon, there is another session that is a twin session of
this one, SIM 19, and of course, we will
keep talking about topics related to
resilience, and you are most welcome to join us.
And the second announcement is that there is also a call for extended
abstracts that goes to the presenters in this session, and we would
be delighted to have your contribution
So,
questions, comments?
Okay, I have Deborah first because he's here.
To Mareike, I guess, and Jose. There you are.
When you talked about sustainability and materials, it made me think of recent
projects and deciding from the beginning, what are you going to do with your
materials and documents, and where are they going to live from a sustainability
aspect?
So if, as David just pointed out, if you
plan for when your project goes away, even though you don't want it to,
from the beginning, what are your options for where you put this stuff so that it
can be searched in perpetuity, it can be accessed, and thinking
about potentials for more than one place.
So just in a recent example I have where everything went to one particular
repository, which is difficult to use, frankly, and really,
really hard to access. So the materials are there, but they're not in a friendly
format that would make all of us get excited about something like using an
LLM to assess that material. And there's very
valuable information in there, but it is now very difficult to access.
So that's another aspect to your
sustainability point.
Any comment back
from Mareike or Jose? No? Then.
Yes,
you're totally right.
So what I'm wondering, it's important for
research infrastructures also, of course, to collect this kind of
information if it is related to the infrastructure
itself. But what you are commenting on is, I think,
regular research data management practices.
So I'm wondering whether research infrastructure should also
be in charge of that when it's coming to
training. So, where can we draw the line?
Thank you.
I think in a lot of the talks, there was quite
a strong contrast between the providers
or the maintainers of a service and its users.
And
that got less so with David's talk.
And I wonder if you have thoughts about how you
break down that dichotomy so that we have more people that consider themselves
part of an infrastructure, so that we have resilience through
wider participation.
Somebody from the panel wants to reply?
Sorry? Can you bring it? Oh, well, David should be
listening, so can we hear him
in case he wants to say something? It's 4:00 in the morning
for David. I know, I know, but he-
He's totally there ... he's there.
Yes. Only the voice. Only the voice. Yes. Not young enough.
Any other questions while we are waiting for...
Oh,
yes.
Just to support what Nikki asked, I think it's really important question, but I
think there is a difference between what David presented when the inputs are
basically intellectual. You invest your time and your brains into making
connections between specimen data and people.
But infrastructure sustainability such as repository and
bot attacks and so on, this requires
things more than time and brain. There is a hardware component.
There is
system ownership that a human which has an extra hour
and a laptop cannot provide. And
I think, Nikki, you ask really, really good question, but I
think it actually forks in two situations when brain and laptop is enough and
the situation when it's not. And I... Yeah.
Can I bring it back to you?
I can't move.
Give
it to me. Is that working?
Yeah. No,
Nikki, it's always cool to do things bottom up, but I think, Ifa, you had a
really important point. You put it in the right wording.
I think about these things, but I've never worded it that way.
We have this lack, really, of
really reliable people in the project.
So a lot of what I, for example, presented today is really handling from
project to project to build this infrastructure.
Disco went a similar way. So,
I'm not criticizing any bottom-up approach, which is super cool, but
we need also some kind of awareness in the
decision-making process, in particular of the European community
and the commission,
that we need sustainable funding for these things to build it up
reliably. Because a lot of people will leave this project.
It's depending on single persons developing this, so this has to
be embedded probably in a wider framework, and then these bottom-up
approaches could work. But what I'm personally
lacking, maybe others are in a bit better situation also, is really
constant funding for the concepts we developed.
So they're frequently shifted from project to project.
I look how can I preserve biodiversity digital twins and
biodiversity meets data and so on.
We have been similar, and some people here in the room have been in similar
situations. So this is what currently working because it's now getting really
serious with loss of data, with losing of the joint infrastructure
network. So
I'm already also advertising a little bit, yeah, more governance
then.
Yes, more governance indeed.
But I think that is still a bottom-up movement
Because we are talking now about institutions.
Institutions are applying for projects, and
we can scale up, of course, that
using the research infrastructures.
And the research infrastructures will scale up and will have
programs that try to avoid that
fragmentation as much as possible.
But in any case, it's still, at that level, a problem.
So in the consortia of research infrastructures,
making those systems is where I see some
solutions, because where the research infrastructures are across domains,
already giving value to the country or at regional level, at
European level, for instance, can make a call and say, "This is the value.
The value needs to be sustained. This is the way to sustain it with
a long-term financial sustainability." So
it's still a bottom up. I don't think
governments will start thinking
coherently in that way. Not yet.
Yes. Do you want to respond?
Yes.
Yes? Okay. You have--
I'll grab it after.
Yes. Okay.
Thanks. Yeah, so I think probably Bionomia was the
strongest contrast you could find.
But I think still, not to have a strong wall between
providers and users is a really healthy thing.
They are the community of people that are
maybe also providing different services, so doing the same kind of thing.
But the more one can learn from each other, the better and stronger we can be.
But also, it kind of depends at what scale you look at it.
So
David and Bionomia is also a user of GBIF, but is such a
strong
push to the way that GBIF has developed in the past couple of years.
So it just depends what scale you look at.
Did you get it?
Yes.
Yeah. Let David answer.
Yeah. Let him unmute himself.
Tell him to unmute.
I'll tell him. Yeah.
Tell him in the- In the chat
Or just in the microphone. Is it-- Can you hear us? Yeah, yeah.
David, can you unmute yourself, please?
Yeah. I'm on Zoom. Is that-- Can you hear me?
Yeah, we can hear you.
Yeah.
Okay, good. Thanks.
I'm so happy that you guys have had this discussion session.
I think it's quite amazing. So I have no particular strong feelings
one way or another about this. But I think Nikki is right.
It's a question of scale. There's going to be
a certain element of any one project, large or small.
Or I just put in the chat something to consider worth
contemplating is what is a fail-safe
and what in your project is safe to fail?
Because if decisions are being made on the margins, as they always are, there's
going to be some component of your project that you find core,
and others that are much more peripheral and might be safe to
fail.
So that's a challenge that I would raise for everyone, GBIF included, is to
contemplate these things and to contemplate what is the core principle that you
wish to espouse.
But at
least what I've done with Bionomia from the very beginning is to recognize that it
will probably fail,
and what should I do to honor the time and effort that individuals have put into
any kind of
expression of themselves into it as much as I possibly can
at the very beginning,
knowing full well that at the end of the project, it will probably die a very
painful death for some, me included.
But otherwise, there should be some persistence to it, and that, for me,
means
minting no new identifiers for anything as an outset, as one
particular principle. The interoperability is paramount.
Okay. Hi, it's Siobhan Leachman. I am the bottom of the bottom-up
process.
I just am
frustrated because I begin to rely on these tools.
One of the reason I'm a superuser of Bionomia is because I use it for
other research and other
manner of pieces of work that I do. And so for
me,
I really admire that David has thought about the
resilience of the project and the possibility that it is going to go away.
But when he says it's painful, I will be crying when it does.
And I get frustrated also that it's just him.
So there's a lot of organizations that use this data and round-trip this data,
and he is self-funding it. He is with his own
volunteer time,
and it is so valuable. Well, I regard it as being very, very valuable to
the community. That's why I've devoted hours and hours of doing this
work,
and I get very frustrated that
institutions themselves don't come in and assist or take it over
or encourage its resilience. Yeah.
That's just my point of view.
Thank you very much.
No. Okay. Very good. Yeah.
All in favor.
I can jump in now
with randomness. Hi, this is Sharon from the Field Museum.
I have a couple of thoughts that percolate with the through thread with
everyone's talks, and first one that comes to mind is we're talking about
research infrastructures. Are we?
Research by its nature is transient, right?
Someone comes up with a hypothesis, an idea, a thought, then there's a project,
then it gets money, and then it's a thing, and then they write their paper, and
then it becomes
their legacy. And then everyone starts talking about how do we keep all the data
around? To my mind, they're different things
Right? And the governance and resilience around research and its products,
I think is part of the problem. That's not the same sort of governance
and resilience and support that data infrastructure
needs, because it just needs to exist, it needs to be supported, it needs to be
paid for.
And as a community, we've relied on volunteers
forever,
and research is getting a really great benefit from it, and it's great.
It's supposed to. But where is the governance and resilience and
care
for those of us sitting at the bottom of the pile, the Davids, the
BHLs, all of these things.
So I think there's parallels, and we need to spend as much time and effort
thinking through that part of this whole puzzle, because it supports
it. The users at the end are great,
but the providers, we need that kind of support.
So there's that, and I kind of see it in the language a little bit.
But if we're talking about research into data infrastructure, okay, that's too.
That's cool. Can we get that to have the same level of
acceptance as skill and talent?
It's not about just making that bit easy, so everyone else can do their research,
in my opinion. So there's that, and the second stream
speaks to community a little bit.
There are things that get saved because they were open in the first
place. And those teams and those people built a community who,
when they had a problem, were willing to step up.
The more research projects that turn into infrastructures that kept
closed and not shared, now you have no one to support you, and all of a sudden,
you're in trouble, and people are like, "Oh, really?
Oh, okay." And you have to scramble.
If we were a community sharing the infrastructures, it would be easier to support
each other
because the ecosystem and the network would have resilience in it,
like
Kit was talking about yesterday. How do we build those?
It's comments, really, more than questions.
But thank you for doing the session. This is really cool.
So there's hands up over here somewhere.
I'm going to give it back to you, and you can choose.
Yes. Okay.
Deborah and then later Vincent.
Vince.
Vince?
Okay.
So one maybe fairly banal observation, one really controversial
observation, and then one genuine question to the panel.
So the banal observation, I think we've all learned the hard way
often in terms of building these bottom-up infrastructures and then
finding some narrative about how we sustain them or, in some
cases, don't. And certainly, the recipe that I've
tried to adopt is basically trying to build a deep institutional
vested interest in the infrastructures that you build, trying to
percolate that to a national interest because there's funding,
certainly at that national level in most places, if you can
tap it. And if you look at the sort of infrastructures that we're often involved
in, that's a frequent recipe that I think we
go down.
So that's the banal observation. The controversial observation, and it was
interesting listening to Matt and sort of the reluctance, for example,
even to introduce API keys to start
facilitating better awareness about who's using our
infrastructures is, I think that knowledge of who's using those
infrastructures and the fact that there is clearly very
substantial demand for these infrastructures is
that that does suggest somewhere someone might be willing to
pay for that data and for the use of
those services if we start
managing that in a more integrated way, in a kind
of community consensus way across the global community.
So I'll throw that one out there, but I realize that is quite contentious.
And then my genuine question is actually about
accreditation within this landscape.
So one formula that I know is often used in the cultural heritage
sector is that certainly in the UK, a number of
infrastructures have gone down the accreditation route, which
basically requires you to have data management
plans, to have a narrative about how you sustain.
It's one that my observation is, I think we as a community
don't use very much, but I'm curious to know if others have
gone down that road and whether that's been of any
value in terms of sustaining the
infrastructures that people have built.
As I say, cultural heritage sector in the UK use that model a
lot, and that helped them to tap into
national funding resources because they have that badge
of accreditation from those external sponsors
who testify to the value of that infrastructure.
So is that a model that we should be looking at more?
Thanks.
Thank you, Vince. I think that they are very interesting points.
And, yeah, if I can answer you, I think that is the
direction we're thriving, accreditation.
And we have some efforts in our community, and there's research
infrastructures that are using that as a mechanism
to involve the community to guarantee this resilience.
I don't know if Wouter, do you want to add something on that around Disco
or...
No.
Yeah.
Just in case, a few words.
Yeah, I don't have much to add there because this is still an
area that I think we need also to develop still in Disco.
I think-
One of the advantages that we have in Europe is that we have
some acknowledgement from the European Commission that
these data infrastructures are important, and there is an
acknowledgement of having these research infrastructures like
Disco and LifeWatch, and others.
And they also say, "Well, governments need to fund that."
And they do, but
governments do not have a lot of money available for that, so it's not
very important for them yet.
We pay taxes for water and electricity, but we don't pay taxes
for data, and that's actually a bit strange, I think.
I think we need to
see, on a national level more, the importance of data and I think
the governments,
the ministries need to invest more in that.
Thank you both. Okay, first-
Can I ask a question?
Yes, you can ask the question. Yes, indeed.
So I think I didn't catch the whole session, just David's, but I
think David is actually
the first point of a curve that this community needs to
anticipate happening. So David innovated a full stack
very cleverly. You heard him think about the technologies.
He's using the most recent technologies.
And what we're seeing is that everybody is going to do this.
A PhD student is going to do this, a master's student is going to do this.
Your friendly neighborhood kid next door is going to do this.
And so David is so far out in front as a solo developer,
single-shot app that made a worldwide difference,
that we're not recognizing that. So what I'm seeing now,
as a development, as a biodiversity informatics group,
is that everybody is publishing their own applications, that there is
problems that we've seen for 20 or 30 years, and now anybody can do them because
they have LLMs,
and they can do the whole stack with a couple of natural language comments.
And those products are very fragile.
Those of us with more experience can see the issues.
But they are innovations and there are contributions just like Bionomia.
So you are seeing the drop ahead of the tidal wave,
and I think the community needs to anticipate how they're going to observe the
rest of the wave that's hitting the world when it comes.
Right? So sustainability, not just one project, thousands and
thousands of projects.
Because it's coming.
Well, sounds very scary.
But-- or promising.
We don't know yet.
It's not scary, it's just like, what do you think about it?
I have a gentleman here, sitting the floor, so and later-
One of the short people. Thanks.
Thanks. I'm
reflecting on exactly what was just said in that I'm seeing two trends
that were articulated here. One is a devolution
of power, control, and infrastructure
from situations like the United States government, where there were entire
departments devoted to certain datasets and things like that.
And now there's a nonprofit that has taken that up, and good luck to
them keeping them going in the face of a world where those
data resources are under
well-meaning, but assault
from LLM-based data queries.
Speaking as an extraordinarily small-scale data provider,
I'm in a position of I don't have a Matt in front of me,
fronting when my data get just
destroyed by queries.
And so the data disappear functionally.
So I'm seeing this combination of two curves going in the wrong
direction relative to each other, of
infrastructural institutions being able to
protect and maintain
the infrastructural resources as they become smaller and smaller scale.
So that's what I'm looking to the folks who are up front there who spend their time
thinking about this and working on this to make me less terrified
about that future and help me think about how I can be a
productive and useful part of that future, rather than one of the little tiny
things that gets clobbered by the LLM agents that are being created.
Go for it, guys.
That was even more scary.
So Dieter and-- Yeah. And
James is there. So
yes. Okay.
Okay, go back here.
Sorry. Okay.
Thanks. And I think I echo Matt exactly
and several others in this room.
But another theme here and a way I think of evaluating this
or trying to make good decisions is that word value, which came up
many times. Right? Things like GBIF have
proven value to the community. GBIF, fortunately, is
underpinned. It has a business model that has
allowed it to survive for 25 amazing years, and we've got 25 more
plus, right?
David is the complete opposite. It's just David.
It's his own money, his own time.
David, through Bionomia, has proven to an enormous
audience the value of that resource.
But it is
not protected, right? David's doing his best.
And so this community, I think what we're saying is we need to assess
value across all of these products that we have before the tidal wave, Matt.
And
this one, I think this is a beautiful case, right?
Who's going to step forward? What infrastructure is going to step forward and say
to David-
It's time to move this into a new framework where we will help you protect this
resource.
And I think the value proposition here is just
that, and we can assess the tidal wave as it comes.
We need that innovation, and we will assess that, and the key point
is, as a
community here, what infrastructures can volunteer
or see that value and will invest in it.
Thank you very much. I think this is a very interesting point
for many of the research infrastructures that are well-consolidated, but not only,
also those that are about to become operational.
For this call could be very interesting discussion internal.
Deborah and Judita.
I think that we will need to stop soon.
I want to say personally, for me, certainly a fan girl of Bionomia from the
start,
that from the beginning, for me, it was about agency,
which is incredibly motivating when you see that you can touch someone
else's data. How else can I get my hands on the NHM data or the Field
Museum data or the Paris Museum data?
How am I going to knock on your door and say, "Hey, I can help you with your data
and make it better?" You say to me, "Who the heck are you?"
Right? And so he built an ecosystem with such a thought
that gave us, yes, we have to have an ORCID, so it's open in a
context, right? And that context says, if you have one of
these identifiers, you can join this party, and you can add your
expertise. And we're always talking about information loss all the time,
institutional information loss, human information loss, right?
And now you've given us a system that thinking about how you give people the
ability to touch your data in a way that allows them to,
one, be motivated by the fact that they have expertise they
can bring to the table and help you.
Anyway, so thank you, David.
Just
one minute. A comment about what was
discussed by Matthew about the fact that
these
crawlers are costing money to infrastructures, and infrastructures need to
invest money to defend themselves rather than to serve their
users. And I was wondering whether there are any
ideas about
recouping the money spent from the offenders.
Because I remember that an open-source project, Write the Docs,
at some point was scraped by particularly aggressive crawlers
that costed them a lot of money because they did have an old
file that was particularly heavy.
And in the end, they reached out to the company who had created this
crawler, and they
sort of pointed out the cost, and they got
their money back. And they wrote a blog post, this
is the reason why I know this story, and they said, "Okay, we learned
a message that we should think about our infrastructures in order to avoid these
things, but we also think that we should somehow
call the rogue hackers to pay back somehow." Is
there any idea that research infrastructures will somehow adopt
a similar strategy? Because
we are talking about open data, but the data are for the community, not for
actors making a commercial service of them without paying back to the
community.
GBIF's got decent funding, so
we don't need to charge people for that data. It's already there. It's free.
If you look in the correct place, you can download it with very
little cost, almost zero cost to us,
especially if you download it from Amazon, Google, or Microsoft's services.
So the problem is more directing the people to the correct place,
which some of these agents just don't find.
But in general, if you're not backed by, in our case, Copenhagen
University's internet connection of however many hundreds of
gigabits and the generosity of the cloud
providers,
then the costs have risen.
And I don't know how you would really do that.
I have read the same blog post from Read the Docs.
They got $5,000 in compensation from the
apologetic company.
But when it's a smart TV that's crawled and you've got all of that,
who is it? You don't know.
Even if
you have a website where you can directly look at the logs, ask the AI
agent, "Look at this webpage and do something," and you can see the
requests that come, and they're anonymous.
I think OpenAI say OpenAI, but all the rest,
it just appears to be usually some major US internet provider.
For GBIF, most of our traffic now is from Comcast, which is the
United States' biggest ISP.
Can't block that without blocking a lot of home users and businesses,
so that's obviously why those companies are also contracting with that
ISP for their connections. It's just
impossible to identify.
The reason people would want API keys is then you can identify them,
then you can do something about it.
We had the BirdAWorld, all those websites.
I can identify them and do something about them.
It's all the rest of it that's hidden and cloaked.
It's just increasing the costs of running a website.
Okay.
Thank you for the answer. The ambiance is a little low now
because of the
complexity of become resilience, but at least we are
thinking about that. At least we are having that as a priority, and this is
something almost new for many. So thank you very much for being
here, for your contributions,
and let's
continue talking about resilience in many, many ways.
Thank you, David. Thank you.
Online, so
even though we
will not have the last speaker presentation,
so we've got a little bit of flexibility at the end how we deal with that. Sorry?
The questions and-
Yeah. How we deal with it, we'll just see how it evolves, I guess.
Okay. Well, welcome to the session,
a series of talks on data quality.
I'm not going to introduce all the speakers. They can deal with it themselves.
That will just save us a bit of time.
So we'll just be able to use the maximum amount of time for the speakers and if
there's time for questions after each
presentation.
So it's a bit of a mixed bag, which is great actually.
Biodiversity is always a good thing.
How are we going for time? Right.
You've got five minutes for the introduction.
Yeah. Well, we don't really need a full five minutes for the introduction, but
we've got to fit in with the timing, yeah.
Just to mention the broad biodiversity
data standard.
Yeah.
There are two presentations on the biodiversity data
quality standard, at least the proposed standard.
It's been expert-reviewed, led by Dag.
And four expert reviewers have done a remarkable job,
and we've spent six months
updating the documentation for that and submitted it back to Dag.
And he's been a bit busy distracted with organizing this conference,
so expect to see that go out to public review.
I would think he's in the meeting next week, so it'll probably be after next week.
And how we handle the feedback from that remains to be seen, but
we'll probably end up using our GitHub repository,
most likely.
Yeah.
Just for those who aren't aware of it, we do have a
workshop after lunch on BDQ that
Paul Morris is going to run. So if you really want to get
down and practical, that's definitely worth
attending.
Paul has done one implementation already, and that's been incredibly
handy
because we thought we had the standard finalized until we ran through test
data
and through a series of iterations on the BDQ standard.
So yeah, if you're interested in the practicalities, I highly recommend
going to the workshop. And Arthur's been passing out some
cards which have the
BDQ website sitting up on TDWG. It's
bdq.tdwg.org.
The namespaces
have yet to be done because we have to have the
standard ratified before the rs.tdwg.org comes
into play.
And there'll be a series of vocabularies and
TDWG's
first ontology related to a standard.
So that's possibly a few unknown quantities
associated with that. But Paul has been discussing it with
Steve Bascoff,
and it'll be interesting to see where that one goes to.
I don't think I have much.
I think we may as well get set up.
Those that don't have the cards, if you grab a card up here in
front, and that'll give you the web link if you want to
later date. There's only there one when you're walking out.
It's not ours.
I was going to say.
That's not ours.
That's not ours. So what the heck's going on?
That's the one underneath it. That's not ours, isn't it?
Yeah.
Yeah. Just
kill that.
I don't understand why that's-
I don't think that's right.
The wrong day.
Sorry?
The wrong day. We should get another folder for today.
Yeah. That's great.
No, do you think?
I can't see it on here.
Sorry.
Yeah, no worries. So-
Someone must have changed it because it was all set up before.
Oh, okay. What did you want to look at?
That's not today.
Okay, so it's from 11 or-
Yep. That's similar.
That's the
one.
That's better.
And then what-
Number one, that's it.
Number one.
Ah, nope.
This one there.
No.
Okay.
That one.
Yeah.
Okay. Great. Thanks very much.
Yeah, no worries.
Okay. We're underway. Just one sec.
Right.
Yeah, first up, I'd certainly like to thank my team members, Arthur, Paul,
and John, for the immense amount of work we've put into this proposed
standard, BDQ.
And
I need to hold two things.
Just a bit of background.
We've heard about a number of bits of AI in the last couple of days.
The bit that seems to impressed me the most is working with
what's now called Gemini Notebooks.
I don't know if any of you have run across it, but I highly recommend it.
It provides you an environment
where you feed a whole background of
video, text material.
I'm not sure if it handles audio, but it wouldn't surprise me in the slightest.
And that provides a local context.
So
in my case, what I've often been-- I found it extremely handy
for is, I can feed the nearly 800
pages of associated documentation of
BDQ as a local context for
it to operate in. And then, of course, you can ask it
questions.
Of course, Gemini Notebooks, it used to be called
Notebooks LLM, I think, prior to that.
But also has the whole Gemini LLM sitting
behind it as well to provide a global context into
that local environment. So it is really quite a brilliant tool.
And because you're dealing with
quite a complex standard in the case of BDQ, it's incredibly
handy to throw a whole series of questions at it,
and I got it to prepare the graphics for this slide right
from the word go, and it did a pretty good job.
I'll buy a coffee to anyone who can find the hallucination in the
presentation.
It produced a hallucination, which I thought, "This is just seriously weird."
And I spent about an hour trying to get it to
do it properly without the hallucination and just gave up.
Because every time I got it to correct it, it produced a totally different series
of graphics.
It was just seriously amazing stuff.
But overall,
well, the other thing that I think is important about the Notebooks LLM is that
the four of us here
are probably the world experts in what we're talking about now.
So we know when there's a hallucination
pops up. So in other words, there's not much
expertise in this particular environment other than ourselves.
So detecting a hallucination is not that difficult.
Okay. So yeah, we would like to
try and get the plethora of various tests
and the outcomes of tests
based upon a single framework. And
one of the first things that we did
was to go out to all of the data aggregators and look at the tests they were
currently running,
like the Atlas, GBIF, iDigBio,
BISON, et cetera. And I think there were
probably over 500 tests that we had a look at and to
evaluate. And it was quite handy because we could start to sort of see the
breakdown in what was going on.
So
the hassle is obviously everyone had their own variety of doing it, so
we needed to come up with, I think, a framework that gave a
unified, transparent, consistent,
justifiable
setup
for you to be able to evaluate
data quality in the biodiversity data context.
Right.
Two hands.
Goes back to 2010 at Woods Hole, where it
became apparent to me, I think I was probably talking to Tim Robertson at the time,
I thought, "Everyone's doing a slightly different thing.
Wouldn't it be wonderful if we could actually come up with a standard?"
And it took us four years to get around to it, and I was in the situation in
2014 of
probably, there were a bunch of us there, and everyone stepped back, and I was sort
of left there to go, "Oh, well, I suppose I'll convene this."
12 years later or 11 years later, we finally
arrived.
I think all of us originally predicted that we probably could solve this thing in
about a year and a half or so.
As you will see, it is a lot more complex than you would
first imagine.
So yes,
the output is
a set of 110 core tests,
and I think one of the key take home messages is you cannot define data
quality without a use case.
So everything in relation to the BDQ standard relates back to
use cases.
Task Group Three in the Data Quality Interest Group
area was tasked with coming up with a
series of use cases.
So we're very much thankful for their work, but also in Task Group One,
led by Alan Kock-Vega,
produced the background of the framework which
BDQ is based upon. We have extended that.
Right.
So really, this just brings together a couple of practical
components, the information elements, which is Darwin Core
speak, but the standard, we've used Darwin Core as the
example, but it's not dependent on Darwin Core or the data
structure. It could be the data package, it could be Darwin Core Archive, it
could be ABCD. It really just doesn't matter.
But we've used Darwin Core as the example.
So you've got a set of information elements like country code going in as the
data. You've got a set of parameters which might modify
how that implementation is done for a local environment.
We've got a set of source authorities that may be used, like ISO
3166,
and then we come up with a series of
structured responses that Arthur will talk about.
And you've got
four different test types. This BDQ FFDQ, which I
hate, but it stands for Biodiversity Data Quality
Framework for Data Quality.
Doesn't it?
Fitness for Data Quality. Thank you, Arthur.
It's a mouthful any way you say it, but you can start to see
there's seven vocabularies and one ontology
underpinning this stuff, and this is part of the ontology.
So you've got a validation, and a good example of that would be,
I've just got a couple of examples here.
Country found would be one example of that.
The amendments propose changes, but
it should not be automatically
processed in the data without some consideration first, of course.
An example of that might be amendment month standardized.
And the terms that I'm using here are part of the standard itself.
In fact, it's one of the vocabularies called BDQ test.
Annotation,
the one I've got down-- sorry, annotation.
Issue, of which the example would be annotation
not empty. And this
brings up a point that in some cases, our tests are what we call
aspirational. In other words, implementing that might be kind
of difficult at the moment, but there is an international standard.
Who runs it?
W3C. W3C standard on annotation.
There is an annotations interest group, and you can talk to Paul about that
afterwards. But that's an example of an issue.
It's just a warning flag saying, "Maybe you better look at this issue."
And the last type is measure,
and an example of that would be validation tests that
have been set to be compliant on that record, for
example.
Oh, another five minutes. Thank you, Arthur.
This is an example of the nature of the response, but Arthur's going to talk
about this, so I'll just say this gives you an idea of the structure of the
response, in other words, a status, a result, and a comment.
But as I said, Arthur will expand upon that one in
the third talk. So the overall culmination is a set of
excuse me, responses for
validations, amendment measures, and issues.
But like the use case, the
report is very much tied in with the actual use case itself.
That provides the context for the nature of the report.
And one of the key issues I'll repeat is the whole transparency of this
system.
And
I think one of the take home messages is that
we really, right from the word go, recognize this as a sort of a
cradle-to-grave strategy,
meaning we'd really like the tests to be applied at
the point of data collection, where errors can be picked up and
usually corrected at source IDs than they can be further down the pipeline,
further down the track.
So things like Specify, et cetera, might be
examples where it'd be lovely to see that implemented.
And of course,
won't be Well, I think it's already arrived, of course.
You just take this in the field, and why not have it all built into your phone or
something equivalent? We've seen a whole series of examples of that in the
last couple of days. But certainly, it applies to aggregators where we
were sort of focusing, I guess, originally.
But also for software developers, the whole setup is pretty darn
modular, and because there's an implementation already, it
is not going to be too difficult. It's quite agnostic, the standard
on how you want to implement it.
And obviously, I think the take-home product is we
really want to see the user community
have a lot more assurance about the data they're getting, particularly from the
aggregators. Because I think if I had a dollar for every scientist that said to
me, "God, there's so much crap data in the system,"
that I would probably be a very rich person.
So that's usually an argument that I've been getting.
So BDQ is very much aimed at providing a
consistent quality check. But remember, it is linked to the
particular use case.
And a practical example of that might be
for your use case,
the Darwin core term day might be totally
irrelevant
for some applications, but it might be incredibly important for others.
So it just depends on the use case. Okay?
So the
test that looked at day might be totally irrelevant to some
use cases in some communities.
Really, that's where I wanted to stop.
Yeah, sure. Yep. Any questions? That's good.
Yeah, time for if there's any questions that I might be able to answer.
The experts are actually in front of you, so if I can't answer.
So yeah, any questions at all?
It was too complex, was it?
Oh, yes.
Oh, sorry. Yes, the microphone.
A quick question. How did you choose the use cases?
Did you run a poll to see what were the most common use
cases or a brainstorming session?
Yeah.
I mentioned task group three in the data quality interest group was
specifically set up to survey
potential use cases, and we've taken some of those.
We've actually added-- I think we've certainly added one,
and removed a few others as well.
So what we've got at the moment is
110 tests,
four or five use cases we have. I can't remember exactly how many.
Sorry? Single record tests.
Oh, sorry. Yes, single record tests. Yeah.
Oh, well, sorry, 110 single record tests. Yes.
I keep forgetting about that.
Four use cases. Four use cases, yeah.
But you'll see there's documentation, and Paul's written a
tutorial if you want to generate a new use case for the standard to add it
in. There is a namespace vocabulary just for
the use cases called BDQUC.
But the methodology for adding tests, because if you add a test, you've got
to also
justify that test by a use case. But Paul's written a
rather good tutorial on that, which steps you right through that process.
So that's where it stands at the moment.
Some of the use cases are quite broad.
Taxon management.
Yeah.
Yeah. Anyway, I can talk to you about the use cases, but they're all documented.
Time seriously up.
I go up in a puff of smoke now,
or Odin comes down and...
Over to John Waller for the second talk, and I'll see if I can set that up.
Can you load it up for me? Okay.
Hello. Yes, I am John Waller. I'm
working at GBIF.
My talk today is about rule-based annotations.
I will just say that
this is all experimental work, so
if you kind of forget this presentation and then go to
gbif.org and say, "I remember there was something about rules," and you look
around, you won't really find it. But at the end of the presentation--
Hmm, I think this is-- I was afraid.
I think this is the wrong...
Yeah, this is one
slide that-
There should be a link
on the- There was a file link.
Oh, I must have sent the wrong one there.
But I have my laptop here if we want to
do a quick...
Oh, sorry. Two files.
Try again.
I think I may have accidentally uploaded the wrong one, actually.
Oh, again. Okay. So the one that's in here is not
correct.
22.3 megabytes. It seems like it's
probably right.
This should
be pretty large. Yeah. Yep. Just...
Oh, dear.
Did it only download one?
It's in Norwegian.
Where did it download to?
Just download it again.
Yeah, I can keep talking about the...
No, that is the one.
Yeah, that is just the one slide. Yeah.
So we should try to switch to your laptop?
Yeah, let's try that. But I'll just keep talking about it.
So,
on GBIF,
often we'll have occurrence records that are like a-
suspicious in nature. And so people keep rules in their head.
So
we'll often get feedback where people will say, "Hey, you have an
occurrence record. This is an amphibian occurrence record.
It shouldn't be
found here in this spot."
Let's say Greenland.
So we have an idea
that you can create
bounded rules to capture this sort of common
knowledge.
Let me log in here now. Let's see if we can get this running.
While he's doing that, did anyone pick up "The Hallucinogen?"
Spelt most, M-S-S-T, on one of the slides.
All right.
Okay, I think we can skip ahead.
Hello, everyone. My name is Christian Dandara, and I represent-
Copyright infringes.
Yeah. So the basic idea is that
you can have a rule, for example, this one.
Yeah.
So you could have a rule, for example, that
rule, amphibians in Antarctica are suspicious.
So how would that rule work? So you could say something like,
so in this rule, all the amphibians occurrence records that exist on GBIF would
be marked as suspicious. And then, of course, any future
records would also be marked as suspicious, of course, in a rule like
this.
But
any, of course, occurrence falling outside of that polygon would not be marked as
suspicious. So let's look at a real example.
So I'm not an expert on elephant shrews.
I just went and looked up, what do we know about elephant shrew
distributions? So Wikipedia says, "Oh, elephant shrews
occur over there." But let's go look at the primary data.
Let's go look at GBIF occurrence records to see.
No, go away.
Go away, Padman.
Okay.
All this startup stuff now. It's killing me.
Okay, now we're back to the presentation. So let's look at the primary records.
So if we go to GBIF, there's one occurrence out in Madagascar.
Aside from it being probably a country
centroid, we can go look at the
data surrounding it, and we go down to verbatim locality.
We can see that someone has said, "Oh, this was later crossed out in
pencil." So since we only have one
occurrence record, we can probably safely say that this
is probably not a real occurrence record there.
So not being a real expert, I said, "Okay, I think I
have enough evidence to say that, I'm going to make a rule that
this occurrence record and any future occurrence record of elephant shrew in
Madagascar are suspicious." And what you're seeing here is a little experimental
tool that I will link to at the end of the presentation for making these
rules.
Click ahead.
Okay, let's look at another example.
So,
as you can probably tell by the name of this species, it's only found in
Mexico. This is, you're probably familiar with this cute little pink
salamander,
that you might find, the axolotl. It has a very restricted range.
So I'm not an expert in this species.
But I know
enough that I could make a rule.
So let's say that we had a map like this.
We went to GBIF, and we saw a lot of points outside of Mexico.
So we might say, "Okay, let's make these rules." Okay.
And that's pretty good, but it doesn't capture any
future occurrence records that might be
coming into GBIF. So a better rule might be if we
did some sort of
anti-distribution around Mexico.
And
one thing to note here is this is not a native species range.
I think this is a sort of powerful idea that surprised me that it hasn't really
been done before. Maybe it has, but the idea is to just mark the areas where you
know it's not going to be, and that's actually much easier than marking the
positive
ring. The negative ring is actually much easier, I've found in practice.
You can be a very non-expert and know that there's not going to be any
wild axolotl in South America. You don't need to be
a huge expert to be able to make these claims.
Okay, so now after we've made our rules, also on our little tool, we can
apply the rules. So we can see how they would be applied in practice.
So here I have something called the Download Annotator.
This is really just more of a demo. If you have a large download, this is
not going to work. If you have millions of records, your web browser is going to
crash. But this is just a demo to get an idea of
how
your rule, what it would do to a download.
And so you can see here we've
flagged all the suspicious points.
These are all just laboratory specimens or
people's pets that have been mated onto GBIF.
And we also have our package called GBIF rules.
This is not on CRAN, so you have to go to the GitHub to get this.
But it will do something more, and it probably will handle a larger
download. So whatever will fit in your computer memory, you'll
probably be able to
filter by rules here as well.
Okay. So
going back to our axolotl example.
So I marked a big ring, but maybe
that ring was ...
There were things within that distribution that should have been marked, but we
don't want to mark the whole of northern Mexico.
We only want to mark the single occurrence record.
So in GBIF, as people may know,
GBIF identifiers are not
100% stable. So,
it's very hard to tie an occurrence,
like an annotation to an occurrence record and have that
persist over time. So the way around that is to scope your
rules
into a little box so that
it'll be robust. It'll be targeting the occurrence record that you want to target,
but it'll be robust against these identifier issues.
So what I've done is just
flagged it according to the dataset key and the basis of record in this small
little area. So a future
axolotl could come into northern
Mexico and not get flagged. So this is how you would mark single records.
A little bit of a hack because of the limitations of these
stable IDs.
Okay. So let's go to complex rules.
So some people in the audience might be thinking,
what about fossils? So,
well, this is a common question I get, but I don't think
... We'll talk about it after. But anyway,
you can create complex rules in this system we have so
far. So you could say, amphibians in Antarctica that are not
fossils are suspicious. So you could not be
flagging records that are
obviously
something else.
And here's an example of a complex rule in action.
So you could say,
there's no non-human primates in Cuba except for fossils.
So you could just make a simple rule that says,
any primate records that you find in Cuba are
going to be
suspicious.
All right. I think, yeah, that's the end of my presentation.
I think I made it in time, even with all the little technical hang-ups.
So,
I think I have time for questions, and this is a link to a
blog post, and you will also link to the little tool UI.
So the current situation is we have this R package.
You won't find this on gbif.org.
And
we're kind of working on getting more rule
makers to come in
to make rules for us. That's the big challenge right now.
It's not very visible on GBIF, so that's one issue.
Yeah.
So yeah, I can take questions now if anyone has one.
Yes, Lee.
I guess an obvious-
Do you want the mic? Yeah.
Yeah. I guess the obvious issue is just spatially is one aspect, but
environmentally is another aspect.
So in other words,
like SDM, species distribution modeling, is using environmental
factors. So basically, I'm wondering whether that's
going to be
possible into the future, I guess.
More complex rules you were talking about, and one would be, well, it shouldn't
occur outside this environment.
Yeah, that might go into ...
Right now we have this simple approach.
So the idea is that
we have a few of these scoping things and a few ways you can make
rules, but you could imagine a broader
rule standard where you would have a bunch of
terms.
Environmental variables could be one of those terms that you could
include in there. Yeah, and that's actually a very interesting
comment.
Yes. We have a mic.
Thank you.
We have one here. I think he was first.
Thank you for a very interesting demonstration.
I was just curious about when
outreach for rule makers.
What if I go in there and set a rule, and then you go there and set a
rule that
does not agree with my rule? Do you have a system for that?
And which, on one hand, could be just we're just
disagreeing,
but it could also end up with a situation where I put a rule on
a higher taxa, and then you put a rule on a lower taxa.
How
does these issues get resolved or ... Yeah.
So right now in the current system,
yeah, if you were to just write two rules and they would conflict, they would just
be conflicting. They would both be saved, and there would just be a conflicting
thing. That would be the history of the...
But we also have a thing that I didn't go because of lack of,
there's only a 10-minute presentation, but I have an idea that's on the little
tool called Projects where you basically say,
"Nobody can touch these rules. This is my
working space." But other people can-- It's
read but not write privileges, right?
So other people could read your rules and they can say, "Oh, what did this
individual have to say about this?
That's interesting that they had this
remark about this." And then also
there's more vocabulary that you could support within Projects.
You could say, "Oh, it's not suspicious, it's some other label,
something else." Introduce some other label that you want to add.
Okay, we have a question from my boss back there.
Oh, we'll save it.
Okay, we'll save it to the end. All right.
He can ask it later.
Yeah, let's find this back here.
Need to change this so the
computer...
This doesn't hear me, I think.
There's one here,
mate.
Done by collector X.
Okay, come in.
It's good to see a nice big audience here.
How do I get rid of that? Oh, it's disappeared.
My name's Arthur Chapman, I'm one of the teams on the biodiversity data quality
standard.
And I'm talking about the reports.
I think you need to start the
PowerPoint, I think. Is that done?
Ah.
Click the next slide.
Yep, that's okay.
Good, that's not set up for
the
slideshow.
What was I talking about?
A lot of this is coming from the user's guide for the standard,
section 3.2.
And I'm talking about the outputs, the reports from the
standards. There's particularly users
that
need to understand
what they're getting out of the
standard and how to interpret that when they get the
information.
Now, as Lee's mentioned, the
test follows a series of
terms that's based on information elements, largely with Darwin
Core, but not necessarily. It can be other
things.
And as Lee mentioned, validation, issue, amendment, and measures, and
they each handle
the reports differently.
So if we look at an example here,
the
test validation event date standard,
the input is Darwin Core event date from a single record.
The question: "Is the value of event date a valid ISO
date?"
And the output, a response describing the conclusions
reached from that record.
So what a test produces,
it produces data quality reports, and as you can see,
produced by software implementing one or more tests.
The form of the report is not specified by BDQ, so if
you're implementing it into your different system, you
can structure the report differently.
But there are certain rules that you must follow.
You must follow a
strict order, as we'll show later.
The standard does specify elements that should be present,
and you can see the implementer's guide for the standard in section
7.1, and a report is expected to include a
response for every test run.
Now, responses from the test, the only normative output structure in this
section,
defined in the BDQ
test concept and use
document, section 4.1,
carries the status, the result, the comment, and an optional
qualifier that Lee had on one of his slides.
How a response is presented to users is not defined by the standard.
Now, Lee had this one, so we've got response status, response
result, and response comment. The response status,
basically,
an operational metadata. It's saying
the run has a result,
or the external prerequisites weren't met, and I'll mention that in a
minute.
You've got a response result, which is the core assertion,
the actual assertion drawn from the control vocabulary,
so it is compliant or it's not compliant, for
example.
The response comment is a human-readable explanation
as to what has happened.
And the response qualifier, which we won't go into much detail,
but it's some of the
structured data describing the uncertainty of complex
issues, etc.
So what a test produces.
Data quality... Oh, we got that one, didn't we?
No, go back a slide.
I went backwards.
That's better. The response shorthand.
These come out of the BDQ FFDQ
response.
And there's three shorthands, the response status, as we
mentioned. So the options are, run has a result, the
external prerequisites are not met.
That's for example, if you're testing it against an
external data source, for example, a GBIF
vocabulary, and your computer's...
The link is down or something at the time.
If you run it again later, it might work.
You've got internal prerequisites not met.
For some of them, you've got amended or filled in or not amended.
The result, you've got compliant, not compliant-
Complete or not complete, and I'll explain where these fit
in later.
Or a data value, such as a metric measurement,
numeric measurement. And the response comment, as we said, is a
human-readable comment as to why
that happened.
So the two
responses, the internal prerequisites not met.
For example, if the data themselves did not meet the prerequisites
of the test to be evaluated.
The test could not be evaluated and will always return this
result
for the same input data. So fixing it requires a
change of the record. For external prerequisites not met, the
test could not be evaluated because an external resource, such as a resource
authority, the GBIF vocabulary,
was unavailable when the test was run.
So running the test again at a different time may yield
a suitable result. So it just might require rerunning
it.
So the outputs, the reports are different for the various
validation types that Lee mentioned.
So there's the validation test reports.
The validation test compare data against known standards or rules,
so the result is expected to be either compliant
or not compliant. It's compliant with your rule or it's not
compliant with it.
For example, validation day in range.
So
there's several examples here. The first one,
day equals 15. There's no months given or no year given.
The run has a result,
and the result is compliant.
And the comment, human-readable,
is that the provided value of DWC day 15
is in range.
So it's between one and 31. Not worried about leap
years or anything.
So the second one,
day equals 30.
But in this case, the month is two and the year
1952.
So run has a result, but it's not compliant because there can't be
a 30th of February in the range provided for month
two and year 1952. The third one
here,
day is 31, the month is not given, the year
1932. So the internal
prerequisites are not met
because you can't say without having a month there whether 31
is a valid record or not.
So the result is none. The comment cannot be evaluated for compliance
because the prerequisites of a valid month and year were not met
for days between 29 and 31.
So the issue reports where Lee mentioned you might have
an annotation in the database.
Issue tests warn that something may need further investigation by a
human,
who decides what action to take. Example, the issue,
data generalizations is not empty.
That's one of the tests.
So
if you've got data in your database that
says data generalizations, DWC data generalizations
is placed on a quarter-degree grid,
status run has result.
Result is a potential issue.
So the comment might be, "Data generalizations contain some
value. These data may have been generalized in some way and
may or may not fit
the purpose for your use."
And in the bottom one, data generalizations is empty.
There's nothing in it. So the run has a result.
It's not an issue,
and
the comment is, "Data generalizations is
BDQ val not empty."
I said
empty is in
one of the
vocabularies because we define empty in a particular way.
So the amendments, similar sort of thing.
Amendments where you might be changing something.
Here's one as example. Day equals 23rd.
So that's amended.
DWC day equals 23rd. It's
interpreted as 23. There's no ambiguity
there.
But if it says day equals X, it might mean 10,
it might not.
So it's not amended. But we do stress that
anything that comes up in amendment,
do not put into your database of record
until you've actually checked it by human.
Otherwise, you'll end up with lots of errors and problems.
So the measure test reports, there's three kind of measures.
Single record direct, directly measures the information
element value and returns a metric.
For example, measure event date duration in seconds.
We won't go into that because that's a complicated one.
Single record derived takes the outputs of other single
record tests and creates metrics.
For example, the number of amendments proposed.
And multi-record
takes the outputs of single records across a data set and
returns metric on those data. So some key takeaways.
Tests define the information elements as input and return a response.
The one normative output structure.
All tests are independent.
Every response carries a status, a result, and a human-readable
comment. And-
The report
forms are for validation, asserts compliance issues, raise
warning flags, measures return metrics, and amendments
proposed
improve values. Unmet prerequisites are distinguished as
internal or external, and measures plus use specific thresholds
let consumers decide the fitness
of the data for their own particular use. Thank you.
Questions?
We have a couple of
minutes.
Hi. So sorry, it's not a question, but I'd like to make a
quick plug for BDQ Email, which
helps you to interpret the
results of BDQ tests.
If you Google BDQ Email, then it comes up, and I'm the developer for that.
We were hoping that you would make a presentation here.
Yeah. It was a closed session.
But I have got something at this time, I could share it at the end.
Will you be at our workshop this afternoon?
I can be, yeah.
Good.
All right. Yeah, we don't have any time for additional questions.
We were going to have a blank at the end, but it turns out the person has actually
sent the video. So we're not actually going to have a
spare bit. Morag, do you want to-
Yeah.
Let's see if I can get this thing going properly.
Thank you.
So we just need to change the presentation.
And now it will be
at least a little bit different, because now we're moving a little bit
from all this with validation to
verification.
What the human
eye and brain
probably for at least some more time is needed for.
Yeah, thanks.
I'm Mor Aronsson from the Swedish Species Information Centre,
and I'm also the node for
our
quality work on observation at our unit
or
for
most of the observation that is reported in Sweden.
Now we will see what...
It should work. These two.
These two. Okay, thanks.
Okay.
What is quality? Very much focus has been on
what species it is.
If the taxonomy is right, it is right named.
But the last, I will say 10 years, it has been more
and more focus also on that the position is right,
especially when you're dealing with
species that have some legal
relationship.
And
if
some of them are red listed, that should be protected,
or as there are something that are
sensitive, it's also very important to know exactly where it is.
So
the position is
hiding the right way, and
since
for us in European Union,
the Invasive Species Regulation come, it's also very
important to know where to eradicate things.
But also the timing, of course, when it
was found.
That's normally not a problem in modern observation
because it's reported when it's found
in most cases. And also
who found it, at least in our national system, you
need to have a personal account. So
you can't really be
Donald Duck or something. You need to be a person with an
email.
And
as
more and more observation is online, there is more
and more question on quality,
and also from
both sides.
People or
agencies and
consult
companies
need more quality and
as I already mentioned, some of the legal acts.
And we also have
the opposite. There are some companies, forest
companies for instance, criticize a lot of,
"Oh, yeah, we can't believe these
orchid positions because
it's just whoever has reported it."
And
today, we also have more and more help of AI,
but we also have
the
backlash of AI, how
much people trust it.
Because
it's still
a border there between to use the AI and
not to use it. So we had to be a little bit careful
in that sense also to be trusted both by the
reporters and by the users. So it's a
learning process by the society
on
the AI.
And
I'm quite sure that for
rather long time still, we need the human eye and brain
to
set the last stamp on the observation that
this is correct.
And what is verified in our Swedish system,
traditionally rare birds,
new species to the country,
extreme outliers or
even
other outliers.
Threatened species has, of course, been also a
bigger focus on, and since the regulation
for invasive species came into force for
about 10 years ago,
those listed species has also been on high concern.
And
those classes we are working with in Sweden, it's
a couple of different,
okay classes. That's everything from,
that is an expert that has
determined a sample up to just that we
believe the reporter.
It could be a known person we know. Okay,
he or she knows this species and have done
lots of earlier records that has been correct.
But this is the scale. And then we have
only one that not approved,
and that's used as little as possible
because we try to have a dialogue with the reporter
to change or get more information if there are some curious.
So that is mainly used for when we don't reach the reporter
or the reporter is dead already or
something.
So
what are we really doing? We have been
doing this,
started already for 25 years
since the Artportalen was started, the first
version of Artportalen.
Our main system has this
verification system already for the birds.
Today,
we also change or we are straightened up
very much around the verification.
We have an education
of all the people that should
verify the observations.
We write a contract with them that they should,
especially those who has right to
verify sensitive observations,
that they
should just keep the information and not spread it,
and also that they should behave nice and
kindly with the reporters. There have been
some exceptions from
that, I can say, because they are a
little bit of the
ambassadors for the reporting systems together with the
support.
So those are the ones who really met
the reporters.
And today it's
close to 500
people that
we have contract with and some do
the verification of observations.
And
Artportalen,
it's about seven and a half million reports
only on that system per year. Then we have other external system
as iNaturalist, observation.org,
some other smaller reporting system also
that
give us information.
We have our herbarium system. We have our other
collections. So it's lots of information or
lots of observation to take care about.
So
just from our portal, and it's about 20,000 observation per day.
And then you see that you have
480 people that take care of them.
And then we have a goal
that we should
reach about 10%. That what we think we have the possibility
to do in the long term
of all those observation, because many observation, we
don't have to care of common species that occur, that they should
occur.
Thanks. They are
normally
okay,
or nobody care about if there are some wrong with them
because it's just those rare species, those threatened, and
these invasive species. But today we are,
overall,
on
a bit above. But if you go to around
the different organism groups, it's
a little bit of a bias there because the birds and the vascular
plants has
reasonably higher
percentage.
But we
try to come there.
But
what we struggle with now or have our thoughts about,
it's how to communicate this between
databases. Because as I said, we have the national system.
It's quite easy, and especially if it's in-house, because
that we have the communication.
But as soon we start to discuss with other
species, how should we communicate with them?
And
everything is more and more connected,
as we already heard on
so many other presentations
these two days so far.
So there are need also for this quality
exchange to
go to the
primary repository for observation, so they change
back, because otherwise the wrong observation is still
circulating everywhere.
So how to highlight problematic strange
observation,
and how to highlight that this is a good one.
And
there are definitely need
for standard for that type of
communication on
verification.
So that's
my main message.
Hi.
Are you publishing the verification status in Darwin Core as well, and
what term do you use for that?
No, we don't. Not the verification standard.
It's just those different classes, and today it's mainly in our
internal system in Artportalen, but
there of course, is need of a
Darwin Core standard for this type of communication,
and I'm looking at some of the guys on the first row here now
because I'm not so much in the Darwin Core work.
So,
I think there are others that is better to answer that question.
If what's possible and what's already there to use.
Very quick one. Yes.
Can you tell us when to use verification versus
validation?
Yeah. We have the same word for
everything until
five, six years ago, I think, because the validation
is what was presented in the first three
presentation here, the technical one.
Just to see if there are date, if there's a coordinate that exist, and
such that you don't need human to
do anything
except set rules.
But verification in our terminology, it's
when we put the human eye and brain in looking
at the observation and set the
reliable status on it.
So that's the difference.
I'll just make one comment. I think one of the key issues here we recognized, of
course, is, well, you really want the reports on quality or fitness for
use to stay with the data.
And
the
annotations is one mechanism, which is already a
W3C standard,
should easily enough accommodate that.
But that's something for
annotations interest group again.
Okay, I think we need to head on with the next one.
Next talk.
I'll get you set up.
Thank you.
You
want
to start?
Can everyone hear if I hold it here? Does it need to be closer? Yeah. Okay.
Good.
Yes. Good. Okay.
Hi.
So my name's Adam Richard Bollands. I'm a research fellow at Kew.
I think this is going to be a bit of a different aspect of data quality than we've
been hearing about so far.
So particularly looking at the way names are managed, and this idea of
transitivity in the name resolution process, um,
and why it's important.
Yeah, and this is some work that I did with Bob, Francesco, Cristina, and
Raphael, colleagues at Kew in the Plants for Health and Biodiversity
Informatics teams.
Okay.
So my work mainly focuses on sort of machine learning and applications
of machine learning in botany, so this is a bit of a side quest,
really. But
I come across lots of different datasets and pulling together lots of different
datasets from different places.
And these datasets are often secondary sources that are aggregating
data from lots of other places,
like published literature and sometimes other datasets and all sorts of things.
And I guess around, I would say, 99% of the time
in this process, people are taking the names that they find, pulling them into
their dataset, and during that, they're resolving those names to accepted
names.
And a key decision they have is whether they can then discard
the original names that they found And these sort of original
recorded verbatim names.
So one of the reasons that this really matters is because,
as I say here, changes in taxonomic judgments mean that name resolution
across different versions of taxonomies
isn't necessarily transitive.
We were interested in
quantifying for how many names this
transitivity property fails.
So we did some analysis of the World Checklist of Vascular Plants and World Flora
Online.
I'm going to give the results from the checklist today, but
actually the results from World Flora Online are more severe.
But in either case, you can read more about both of those in this
paper that we published
earlier this year.
Okay, so what am I talking about?
Transitivity, nice mathematical property for certain things
like greater than and less than is transitive,
inequality isn't transitive, and then there's things like, I think,
the relationship that you get from rock, paper, scissors is a anti-transitive
relationship. But anyway, as it relates to name resolution,
if you have some taxonomy and you have a name,
so version one of your taxonomy,
and you have a name x, if that resolves to some name y in
your taxonomy,
and then you update your understanding and you update your taxonomy
in the future to version two,
and that name y then resolves to some name z.
This process is transitive if,
in
version two, the original name x also resolves
to z.
Now you can imagine that this
breaks for things like heterotypic synonyms.
So if in version one x is a heterotypic synonym
of y,
and then at some later point in time it's considered that those two type specimens
are
actually different taxa, then x might not be resolving to
z
in version two.
So this is important to consider for building data sets, because
at the time of version one of this taxonomy, if you
build some data set, you find
the name x and you resolve it to y, then when someone comes along in the future
with an updated taxonomy,
if they're then resolving y to z, that might differ from
our current understanding of how x should be resolved.
So yeah, we were interested in
how many names this fails for and if there's any patterns in the
places and ways that this fails.
So start with an example from the World Checklist.
So
version 10 from 2022,
this name, Panicum nitidum, resolved to Dichanthelium
dichotomum. Jumping forward to version 14
in 2025,
Dichanthelium dichotomum is still considered to be accepted and so it resolves
to itself.
But according to version 14,
the original name, Panicum nitidum, should actually resolve
to Dichanthelium nitidum.
So this isn't transitive in this case,
and I think shows that when you chain the
resolutions in this way, you get this-- assuming that version 14 is correct
anyway, chaining the resolutions in this way gives you this
error,
and so it's important to be preserving the original names.
So
an overview from the results that we got for comparing these
two versions of the checklist anyway.
If you take all the names, at least all the names that resolve to
something,
in the version 14, 2022 version
of the World Checklist, there's around 1.4 million names.
Then if you do this process, the two outcomes disagree for around
13,000 of those names, so around 1% of the names.
Around half of those disagreements occur at the species level, like the
example I just showed,
but then this can also be more severe, where you get disagreements at the
genus level as well.
So
if you were to come across a data set from-- well, in
2025 anyway, if you were to come across a data set from 2022
that only contains accepted names and they've built it in this way by aggregating
data from other sources,
and then you resolve these accepted names to your version of the
taxonomy, you can expect an error of around
1% or 0.5% depending on how you look at it, but let's say
0.5% error at the species level in some of your records.
Which might seem quite small, but this is just from the way the names have been
managed, and I'm sure we're all aware of all the other sources of noise and error
in
biodiversity data.
So one of the things we wanted to look at was if particular groups
of names or species are particularly affected
by this.
And so if you look at the accepted names associated with botanical
regions,
and the accepted names that are involved in these kinds of non-transitive
resolutions,
you get this graph on the left,
and then the residuals from this regression are plotted
On the right,
I think one thing that's quite clear is that there's this clustering in,
I guess, western southern Europe.
I've highlighted France, Italy, and Spain up here
as particularly strong outliers.
Personally, I don't have an idea why this is the case, but I'd be interested if
anyone has any thoughts on that.
So yeah, as I said before, an error of around 0.5% might
seem quite small, but if you're, say, for example, building a data set,
or looking at a data set of Western or Southern Western European plants from this
region, maybe just European plants in general,
this error is likely to be higher.
So
this has just been a snapshot at a single point in time,
comparing the 2022 to 2025
versions.
The analysis we initially did was at 2025, where this line is, and I've
recently updated this with
versions 15 and 16 from
2026.
But yeah, this graph is basically showing that if you take an initial version of
the taxonomy and you jump to future versions,
this kind of error
gets more severe as you get further from the initial point in time.
So we might get a 0.5% species-level error in 2025
when we're looking at the
data set from 2022.
But by the time we get to
June 2026, that's now 0.7%.
So yeah, this, I think,
starts to become a more severe error.
I guess I have the sense that this is something that's relatively well understood
in nomenclature and taxonomy
worlds.
But
hopefully useful to put some numbers to this and
also raise awareness of this more broadly.
I think I've kept well to my time there. Thank you.
If anyone has any questions, I'll try my best to answer them.
Questions, anyone?
Stunned.
So, to summarize, your suggestion would be always keep the original
names so that you can rematch them against the most current.
Yeah, so that's the main takeaway.
Always keep the original information so you can always redo the matching against
the latest list. Yeah. Okay, thanks.
I should have in my last slide.
Yeah, I'm just in a rather tricky case
around
this with one grass that has
four different
accepted scientific names in
four of the different Nordic countries, and
perhaps
all of them could be right in the worst scenario,
because it's
a little bit about what taxon concept
you deal with.
If you accept that it's the same as in Siberia or not,
or the same in Greenland and so on. So,
that's a dimension. Till,
a pun on that, have you
had some thought
around that tricky thing?
I wish someone else was here to answer that. Do we still have time for questions?
We do.
My background is in
maths, really, but
I'll try my best. So my understanding is that you're
starting the original name that someone identifies it with.
That's useful. That relates to the taxon concept in a
useful way,
that gets lost through this sort of chaining process.
That's also reminded me that, as well, I should mention that this is looking at
chaining
this kind of resolutions with just one particular taxonomy.
But that's quite a controlled environment in some ways, that
people can pick up a data set and then resolve it to their own taxonomy, and I
think the error is then
even greater. I don't think I've answered your question at all, but maybe someone
else can.
Perhaps
nobody really can answer it.
Okay, good. Thank you.
You summed it pretty well up. Yeah.
Thank you.
Thanks, Adam.
Great.
I'm going to set up,
see if I can figure the video out to run for the last talk.
I just had a message that lunch has been moved from the first floor to the third
floor.
Yes, that's right. And the door is outside Sal B.
Yeah, Room B.
Apart from the PDF ones, I assume it's still moving.
Yes, that's it.
Hello, everyone. My name is Krisztián Dan Bara, and I represent Natural History
Museum on behalf of the OSCA Consortium.
My talk today is about harmonizing biodiversity data using the
Darwin Core
data standard.
I think by now you've understood multiple
technicalities of Darwin Core,
and I think my presentation will highlight
the value of Darwin Core in the context of our
consortium.
So the OSCA mission, OSCA stands for Open Scientific
Collections Austria,
is about digitizing the Austrian natural history
collections
as they are preserved. So we are targeting preserved specimen over,
today, 15 different institutions.
That includes museum universities and scientific institutions across
Austria.
So the collection is about
creating digital twins for preserved specimen.
You can find a lot more information under our website, which
is osca.science.
Darwin Core is essential for our collaboration
because
all our scientists understand Darwin Core data standard, which
enables us
to collaborate seamlessly.
Also,
it enables us to create institutional interoperability.
These are
situations where some smaller institutes don't have a high
IT development capacity or IT production capacity,
and larger institutes have this talent and knowledge, and they can
collaborate in creating micro infrastructures,
enabling them to
produce and deliver digital specimens
in our infrastructure,
which is nationally available.
We are based on a cloud infrastructure because
we'd like to enable all these 15 institutes
across Austria to collaborate, and cloud was just the best fit
for such an implementation. At the core of our
cloud
stays a centralized cache or a centralized database
that hosts all our digital
preserved specimens into
one large Postgres table.
We are keeping it up with the Darwin Core standard and with
all the approved and validated extensions, so as to enable
as much data production as possible.
Because we are on a cloud infrastructure, we are able to create
coherent workflows.
This, in our context, means that all of our 15
partners
can produce data according to our standards of
quantity and quality. I'll explain this later.
And there is a streamlined process,
where the scientists can not only prepare the data, but
easily
push the data through this pipeline and have it present in
our public portal.
Across this pipeline, we have automated processing, so
it's not only that the scientist produces data, but we have
helper functionalities where this data is
automatically analyzed in terms of, for example,
Darwin Core validity or
essential data value presence. This enables
scientists to understand either errors
or lack of essential data
in their upload phase,
and we enable a feedback loop of testing and
correcting before the data is being published in a portal.
This includes automated processing, of course, under the fair principle and, of
course, with the scientists always having the last expert decision, so
we always have a human in the loop.
Why do we do this?
It's because OSCA is not an oversight
consortium, but a collaboration consortium.
And of course, the institutions previously
and in parallel run other projects which produce
a lot more digital specimens. Not always
digitizing preserved specimens, but sometimes observations and sometimes outside
our scope of research.
But we like to enable scientists to have a
cross-spectrum picture of their output
and their colleagues' output.
So we recognize and collaborate
with the existing data in international
infrastructures like GBIF, Disco Nodes, or even Open
Science.
And so how do we enable the scientists to
get this spectrum of
understanding about their data and their interest
in the data is through our public portal.
We currently run two versions of our public portals, one that
consumes multiple
search and discover APIs from the previously mentioned international
portals,
and a newer one, which enables cross-portal collaboration, and
I'll demonstrate this in a second.
But it is essential to understand that we have three pillars,
search and discover, direct Darwin Core export, because we want to
enable the scientists, once they
identified relevant data to their research, to download it and
maybe process that offline on their computer.
It comes in a form of Excel table.
And we are constantly
trying to understand the gaps between what scientists need and what we offer, and
this is through a constant feedback loop that happens within a consortium and with
third parties occasionally in our public events.
So as mentioned, we're having two portals.
Our current portal is in version four, and the
newest
testing idea is in version five, and I can show it
to you.
So the portal number four looks like this, and
actually, we can test it here. So
we can look for a taxon, and the portal will search through our
own database and through international portals,
and compile a minimum set of
data, but a maximum set of
retrievable results.
This is a mix, and of course, we have enabled filtering to better
understand
and
focus more the result sets.
Portal number five, similar principle, but it
searches through our
consortium data first. So the pink stuff
here that you see between portals is the data that's hosted in our cloud
infrastructure. We closely collaborate with Disco, so
the data is very relevant and periodically harvested into the
Discover platform, and therefore, we
enable this API as well. So this is the local
perspective. And then we have
deep link searches throughout external portals,
which enables the scientists a full experience on
this new portal with the
set of
all enabled filters,
which we believe is an enabler rather
than a compiler of data.
We're still analyzing pros and cons of each approach,
and so that's why we're running with both portals.
Apart from the portal, our own data is
segmented into several
layers of quality. So what's important is to
identify data internally, because when we're looking at
an occurrence detail,
identifying it internally allows us to
retrieve it easily. We can, of course, download it, but it allows us to
also collaborate internally on data quality and data points.
Then we're having a second layer of
quality, which maps MID's relevance
fields based on MID's classes. So
here, based on the
minimal information description
standard, we are
displaying the
levels and the relevant data
around those levels. In our understanding, if at least one
data point in one of these
classes is present, that
requirement is fulfilled. So
we're not computing anything, but we're just categorizing things.
And of course, you see Darwin Core relevant fields,
and their values as recorded in the database.
At this point, I'd like to thank all the 15 institutes for understanding
and adopting the Darwin Core standard.
It was this amazing joint decision that enables us to
overcome barriers and unlock potentials.
And I'd like to also thank all the scientists involved
in making this happen. Thank you very much, and wishing you
an amazing continuation of the conferences.
Thank you very much.
I've got no idea if the technology is working, but Christian is supposed to be
online.
Is that true?
Yes. Hi, everyone. Thank you for
listening to my presentation.
Members of AO-
And thank you for accommodating my online presence, so greetings to
everyone.
Okay, we've got a few minutes for questions. Anything for Christian?
You all want to go to lunch.
I just have a
quick one.
Okay.
Oops. So did you say that you were assessing the quality of the data using the
MID's standard
measurements?
Yes. So it's our ambition to
enable at least MID level one standard of
quality data. So we define quality as both
data being present and data being correct.
So this is a bit of an uphill thing. We approach our data
in terms of key value pairs. The keys are Darwin
Core,
the values is whatever the scientists produce.
So we trust 100% the scientists knowing what they do, because
we run regular training workshops with
this.
And so
if enough key value pairs are met under the
categories I've shown in close to last slide,
then we would compute a MID level.
And we are striving for MID level one, at least.
Mm-hmm.
Now, MID level two is ideal because it also includes media, and media is
extremely useful for our
publicly available
portals. So to clarify a bit the context, we're building this for
scientists, but since we're funded by the Austrian government,
they said we need to produce another value for Austria itself.
So what we thought about is if the data is public anyway,
adding media will be an added value to citizen science,
and therefore, we are like MID level one is the minimum, MID level two
is desired.
Yeah. I think that
my
issue maybe is that the presence of data
might not also correlate to the quality of the data.
Sure.
But having something there is indeed better than not.
Yes. So this is a running question also in our consortium.
So the reason why I'm online is that tomorrow starts our annual
two-day
conference where we have workshops approaching this.
Yes, presence of data doesn't equal high-quality data.
We enable scientists to
correct mistakes.
So there's always
the automation
that I mentioned
highlights presence, but quality is always a scientist
input and usually
inside the consortium, we constantly review the quality of our data, and we're
trying to correct as much as possible.
Thank you, Christian. I think we're going to have to draw the session to a close.
Mention the workshops in meeting room five. Ah, yes.
Workshop on BDQ is in
meeting room five. That's straight after lunch, if anyone's interested.
You're all welcome. Exactly. Well, thank you all for coming.
I hope you got something out of some of those talks at least.
Enjoy your lunch.
Up front,
Giff, Picture 8, Atlas Living Australia, Pensoft, BioShare, and EarthKate.
Thank you guys for your contributions and making this thing happen.
We appreciate it.
So we'll be monitoring the chat in Whova?
Whova. Whova. And so people can ask questions there.
After each session, if we have time, we'll ask for questions.
If not, we'll do all the questions at the end, depending on how the schedule goes.
Sound good? And if you're a speaker, I would love to be able to pronounce your
name, but if you introduce yourself,
that would be fantastic. Sound good? And you'll come up.
There's a pointer here, and
yeah, why don't we get started. Sound good?
So first up
is... Let's see. All right.
One.
Sure
I promise I'll get this.
Thank
you.
There we go. All right. Fantastic. I'll sit. You can go over here.
I'll sit over here. Sounds good. Go for it.
Thank
you.
Hello, everyone. My name is Sara Araújo.
I'm a marine biologist working at the University of Aveiro
in Portugal, and I'll be presenting the Aurora Shiny app, a
tool developed to help standardizing messy biodiversity data sets according
to the Darwin Core.
To start with a small introduction, biodiversity data are often stored
in diverse structures, which makes standardization and
publication through public repositories challenging.
These repositories, such as GBIF and OBIS, require data to be
compliant with the Darwin Core standard.
But the standardization process can sometimes mean
overcoming complex event structures, taxonomic ambiguities, and
geospatial inaccuracies, which can make this whole process
effort, time, and resource-demanding.
Many researchers indicate this step as one of the main
barriers to publishing their data.
And it was with this in mind that we developed an online application
based on R Shiny
that offers a comprehensive and user-friendly workflow for
converting unstructured biodiversity data into
standardized Darwin Core
tables ready for publication.
Through this QR code, you can access
the tool's website. The Aurora Shiny app requires only an
internet connection to work, and the workflow is
structured around eight key steps, which I will be going through
in the next slides.
And to start with the first one, the Aurora Shiny app allows users to
upload their data as a CSV file.
And their tables can then be transformed to a tidy
format if necessary, so one
occurrence per record.
The tables can be uploaded already in a tidy format or transformed
through the application.
The data set can then be inspected before completing the ingestion, just
to make sure that the data was read correctly.
Then user-defined headers can be mapped to the
suitable Darwin Core term,
and this can be done either following automatic suggestions
or manually.
Even following automatic suggestions, users should always ensure
that the right term was
associated with their header.
The app also allows users to create key fields within the application, including
ID fields such as Occurrence ID or Events ID,
remarks fields, and dependency fields.
These dependency fields include, for instance, the
creation of sample size units if sample size value is
already present in the data set.
The workflow also includes the validation of required terms, and the set
of these required terms can be adjusted
by selecting the target submission repository.
So currently, users can choose between OBIS, GBIF, and
EMODnet Biology as their target submission repository.
The tool also allows the transformation of temporal information
and geographical coordinates to the formats required by Darwin
Core.
And then
taxonomic information can be cleaned in the next step so that
the core taxon name is
isolated in one column
with all the additional information stored in the other appropriate
Darwin Core fields if possible.
This clean taxonomic information
can then be validated through Worms if we're talking about marine
organisms, or through GBIF taxonomic backbone if we're talking about
terrestrial organisms. And this process
allows for the
correction of small misspellings,
the resolution of ambiguities, and also the retrieval
of associated information from the taxonomic record output,
including the scientific name ID or the taxon rank, for
instance.
Then the flat table uploaded can be structured in an
event core and an occurrence extension tables,
depending on the fields present in the data set.
And the app also allows the creation of
an EMOF table, an extended measurements or facts extension table,
already in a tidy format. And for that, users need to identify which
measurements are associated with events and which measurements are
associated with occurrence. So in this example, for instance,
temperature would be a measurement associated with a whole event,
and life stage would be a measurement associated with single occurrences.
Then measurements or facts can be edited within the app
in order to be populated with controlled vocabulary.
Data then goes through
a quality control step that provides processing logs, summary
outputs, and
the flagging of any issues that might have occurred along the standardization
process. And after going through this quality control
step, the
Darwin Core tables are ready to be exported,
and they then can be used to create a Darwin Core archive
through
the gbifscipt.
The final step. In the final step, users can
fill in and export a metadata form that was created
based on the GBIF IPT format
in order to streamline the creation and
revision of the metadata associated with
the resource.
So the final output of the workflow are
standard-complying Darwin Core tables and structure metadata,
allowing for a Darwin Core archive to be built and published in
accordance with FAIR principles.
There's some small points that need to be kept in mind, including
that the Aurora Shiny app does not
directly create a Darwin Core archive.
It helps users generate the core data files and
to compile the metadata, but the Darwin Core archive itself
needs to be built through the GBIF IPT.
Also, the tool was
primarily designed to create
an event core associated with an occurrence extension and a name of extension,
or an occurrence core with the name of extension.
Currently, the app does not support the creation of any other type
of extensions, which is definitely
an important improvement to consider for future versions of the
tool.
Other improvements also include the adoption of the Catalog of Life
as GBIF's
taxonomic reference, and also the inclusion of the option
to save the process once the standardization has started.
One final note is that the use of this tool still requires users to
be familiar with their data and to know their dataset well, and
also to have a somewhat basic understanding of what the Darwin Core
is.
We still believe that this tool represents a valuable
tool
to help making standardization of biodiversity data
more
widespread.
This tool was developed as part of the Aurora project, which was funded by the
European Union through the DTO BioFlow project,
and it was very much a team effort.
And just as a final note, we also developed other resources as part of this
project, including a user manual and a video
tutorial for
the Shiny app.
And also the source code for the app is publicly available
on GitHub.
And we're welcoming any suggestions to
improve the tool.
Thank you for your attention.
Any
questions?
Could you define messy data a little bit more specific?
How messy could the data be? For example, if I give you
a primary description of a species and there's a section, other
specimen looked at or something, could you just
produce a Darwin Core out of that?
No, there's some minimal requirements
for
the app to be able to work.
So
we define messy as an occurrence
table, but not standardized according to
the Darwin Core. So
all the information needs to be present in the dataset already,
with some small exceptions.
The users can create key fields, for example,
occurrence ID,
but the information needs to be present in the dataset already.
So,
yeah.
Thank you.
The resolution of taxonomic identifiers,
it looked like it was automated,
but it was not.
So you had
a table with some species, and then there were
suggestions for
complete records from a backbone,
and they were fetched directly from the backbone, or they were already
present in the source dataset?
They were
Okay.
So either occurrence or
Okay. Thank you.
The IDs were one of the fields that can be retrieved
from the taxonomic record and added
to the dataset.
Okay, thank you.
Anybody else?
We can move on, I think.
Was it?
We can move on.
Yeah. Move on. Thank you. Thanks, Sarah.
And
I do have one note. My co-moderator who I just met, I got his name wrong at the
beginning, and so
this is Andreas, not Alessandro. Alessandro is a speaker.
This is Andreas, co-moderator, just to make sure I'm clear. All right.
Next person
is Walter.
Here you go.
Hello.
Why don't you have a sit? I'm going to sit over here this time, and then we can
start
real quick.
So good afternoon.
Today I'm going to talk about
the Global Genome Biodiversity Network,
and
I hope this works.
Yeah. GGBN is about biobanks, and
actually it
has a long history already.
It started in the end of the 2000s, and the
infrastructure was built
around 2010,
and some components of that
infrastructure need to be replaced now, and among them, the
taxonomic component.
Just a few words about GGBN itself.
It's not only a
data collector and data access point, but it's also a
community instrument to actually share documents,
experiences, best practices, all the things that
are related to
samples that are used for DNA-based research,
policy documents, et cetera. So,
it's more than just a collector of data, but we are talking
about this thing. There is a just
this month published white paper that really
summarizes everything that you might
want to know about GGBN and its current
structure and the things it's doing.
One very important point in that paper is how GGBN relates
to global infrastructures. And so,
please have a look at that. We are going to focus here on
the taxonomic component, which I've already said is a bit
outdated. And
what we get from the providers of data is the usual
GBIF type data set in Darwin Core, ABCD or
whatever,
which contains a scientific name, obviously, and it
contains,
hopefully and many times, some classification
information,
like a family name or something, or even an entire
hierarchy.
And as usual, you have those problems we've just heard about.
You get data that it's not really up to the definition
of the scientific name data field, and you have to
deal with it somehow. And of course,
providers should correct that in some way.
They should get feedback also from the platform,
but that's always something that might take some time, and
a database that only deals with E. coli, as doesn't
really see the necessity to put a name on every
record,
which is always the same then, of course.
So,
what should be there is some automatic
processing of these names so that they get online fast,
even if the feedback process takes some time.
And so, we want to implement some correction
process that actually allows that.
On the other hand, that has to be transparent, so the providers
as well as users have to see what happened.
So,
the purpose of doing this is, of course, to improve searches
in the portal,
so that you can look for all kinds of names
related to the samples you are
actually searching for. And also, you
should be able to go through higher
taxa to find your samples. And we will also want to have
some things like gap analysis in the future or something that we can
see, "Well, we have only one virus in the database.
Is that correct?" Among 200,000 names,
at least. So, yeah.
Here we are. Okay. And,
as I said, the current solution needs to be
replaced, and we want an automated workflow there
that will really help researchers to find their materials.
We went out and looked at existing
mechanisms, and I've been working with the project, the Tetrix
project. I also presented last year here
on several things that can be done
to improve quality of names in source data sets.
And we actually thought that it would be helpful to actually
have a parsed out name
to start with, so that we can actually incorporate things like higher
taxonomy in the name matching process.
And the two parses that are out there is the GBIF one and the
Catalogue of Life one. Both supposedly are based on the same
software core, but they actually produce different
results. And after some testing, we
have decided to use the GBIF one for initial
parsing of the names we are getting in.
There is a number of
attributes that actually qualify the type of
parsing that has taken place.
The
ideal one is this one, so it recognizes the name,
and that can actually be processed directly.
We can add higher taxa from the source and then put
this into the name matching process.
With the other things, for example, if it says virus cultivar
candidatus, we know which code it belongs to, so we can add the
attribute of the code. And all these things actually
will need some feedback with the users or a
look of a person in the end to decide if this
is something.
So we will have to input actually
processing routines and perhaps some
human input as well,
in these places where we can actually change parameters and
improve the entire name parsing process.
And we will have feedback at these places in the
diagram.
Looking at the target
name matching service. So this was the parsing, now comes the name
matching.
We have to
use something that can actually address different data sets.
That's the other side of the parsing process.
You have the process itself, and you have the data set
you're matching against.
And
we actually had these criteria for this
matching process tool. And actually, we
came to Checklist Bank name matching as
the most promising
thing we could use. You can use several different data sets if you
want to. And you can actually
communicate with people that are still in development.
And so if you find some things that don't work,
you usually get a response.
The choice for target data set is
practically the same. We came to the same conclusion as GBIF now.
If we have multiple taxa, et cetera, we need something that brings
as many names, as many higher taxa groups into one
data set, and that's the Catalogue of Life in its extended
edition now. So we can get synonyms from
it, which we need for searches. We can get
cover of all organisms with some gaps, as we all know, but
it's still the best, I think, that's in place there.
And we can have a standard higher taxonomy to
offer a good way to search for higher
taxa in the interface.
Further processing is, there are several items that we
get out. It's of course the original scientific name, which in the end,
we need to link back to the unit sample because we have
normalized the names in the first place, so we
have unique names. So we need
that. Then there is something called the match type.
That's again, a kind of qualifier as well as the match
issues. These are standardized terms that tell us something about the
outcome and how the matching was done.
And,
of course, there's the status of the name, if it's accepted or
synonym, and an ID we
hope is unique and resolvable
even in the Catalogue of Life extended edition.
There's still some discussion about that.
Trial and error.
One thing is very important. This pre-processing before the parsing
can really improve the entire process significantly.
And there are things like, for example, if you exclude something like
sp.,
then you get a generic record and that just runs through. If you have the sp.
in there, you get all kinds of things.
And there are other things that are really simple.
You can flag things that are
with cf. and things like that,
identification process specific terms can be excluded.
And this is
a process. That's why there was this star in the beginning.
We have to work on looking at the results.
Okay. And there are, of course, some shortcuts.
So if we are looking at the parsing result, that will be formatted
in a Catalogue of Life data package, data format, not as
a package, but as a table, as this unified
table Catalogue of Life data package provides.
And the exact things go directly into taxonomic enhancement, which is
nothing more than looking for the synonyms and the standard
higher taxa, and go into the backbone for
GTPN. But if it's variant and higher taxon, it can
often also go through if you did the-- oh, I still have
five minutes. That's a lot.
So
because if you cut out these things like sp.
and so on,
there's just not
so many variant things anymore. If a higher taxon is
recognized and it's a correct name,
then it
can also go right through.
And then you have these ambiguous things, which
result in more than one hit in the Catalogue of Life database,
and these could be homonyms. And there we really have a problem.
We have to decide what to do there in some way.
And one plea I have for the Catalogue of Life developers, et
cetera, is it would be possible to actually create
a universal homonym list. And that
would be so helpful in many respects if you have
multi-regnal
mixed data. And I think now we have the data to create
that, and somebody just would have to do it.
I tried to ask an artificial intelligence to create it,
but it refused because it was just a bit too much data.
But
it's possible, I think. So,
again, provider feedback, if we can't really decide what to do,
and especially if it says
none, that means this is not a scientific name,
the parser things. But we should have already excluded those from
the
matching tool. Sorry, I always mix these up.
The matching tool says that's not a scientific name.
This should not be the case because we already excluded those in the
name parsing process.
Yeah. Okay. So
we can actually
Also, of course,
increase things like that. Once we have an accepted name, we
go for things like links to other
providers and provide that information also on the
website, always with a series of caveats.
So on the website, as it is now, practically, you give
in a name,
it's found in the GBIF backbone to be a synonym of
something. You have the accepted name there.
So the accepted name is assigned to the
result object, but it says also what's the
original name, and the original name is another
synonym in this list. So
the way how we got to the accepted name is
documented, and people can look it up.
Because,
essentially,
if the identification is wrong, you can do whatever you want.
And, of course, there are also some concept
problems in doing these type of things.
And
always, if you're using it as a base for your research,
then you have to actually look at things in depth.
Thank you very much, and thanks to these people.
Questions? Okay.
Any questions?
No, we're good.
All right. Fantastic. Thank you, sir. All right. Let's see.
Next is Alessandro.
I don't know if it's the last version of my presentation.
Oh.
Because I already-
Okay
... loaded in this one.
Is it this one?
Yeah. I just downloaded them. You want to see?
No?
Okay. It's okay. I got it. Right here.
Okay. Let's see.
Should be right here.
You know, we also actually can-
I have it.
Let's see if we can...
This is the next one. This is it. Okay, great.
There. Thank you. Oh, thank you.
Sure.
Thank you. And
my name is Alessandro Gioni from CNR, Italy,
and representing in this moment ELTERA Research Infrastructure.
First of all, I want to
describe the ELTERA Research Infrastructure.
It is a pan-European research infrastructure,
and the mission is to
study the
ecology in terms of long-term ecological variation.
And
the study is about structure, processes, and functions
in terrestrial, freshwater, and coastal, and transitional ecosystem.
At the moment, ELTERA is
in Europe, is entered in
ESFRI road mapping 10 years ago. And I
hope, we hope to finish the
trip
in the next
month.
Again, is a distributed
infrastructure with a real in situ
site or facilities that collect a
lot of
ecological parameter.
This is an example of
the site.
This is an example of a distributed
site for
European countries, but also external point is
a site that some
European countries
use for collecting information for other countries.
And this is an example of a
sheet of
the site with a description, name, and so on, and
also the part of
geographical point.
In
the site or in situ facility,
the people collect a lot of type of parameter,
ecosystem, chemical parameter, and soil or
atmospheric parameter, and also biological parameter, but is
not only the part of
the parameter that is collected in the
site.
And for this session,
I want to say what is the
possibility to share this
type of
observation or parameter collected,
and the solution that we have in ELTERA RI
is a data template with a different
table
about the method, reference station,
event, sample, and
one about the license and
data.
It's also provided as a CSV format,
and altogether is collected
using
a zip file,
for collect altogether the information.
The data template
is a data specification that can contain the description of
required information, field, and templates
data. And for more information, it's possible to
download also the specification and
the document in
Zenodo.
This is an example of data template with a
table.
Again, it's like a relational database using the
CSV,
with some data, station, method, and
reference. This is an example of data.
It's possible to store data using data row and data
column in different shape, but the same
information.
What we have done at the moment
for enhancing the interoperability, then started standardization and
fairness, and also in the relation with
Darwin Core format.
And we are mapping this type of
information using Darwin Core terms, and
we try to develop a
data package generator.
It's just an R
function
as an example of the possibility to
transform our data in data package.
This is a
table. We produce a list of
terms that is like
a field of a different table in our
template. And
for each term, as is possible, we have also
Darwin Core match, and the URI, and some
example
for our different unit for different terms.
And this is
the
R
script or function in order to transform
our data in
data template, in
data package, using the approach of
frictionless.
And that's all. I wanted to final remarks to the
point of view of ELTER. ELTER data reporting format
provide a common framework for integrated heterogeneous
ecological observation across site and domain.
And semantic enrichment
through controlled vocabulary and Darwin Core alignment increase the
visibility of ELTER data. And
in the future, automatic publication of workflow enable
ELTER dataset to become
FAIR more than actually
situation. And thank you so much for your attention.
That's great.
Any questions?
Yes, ma'am.
Hi. So thanks for the talk.
So I see that you are trying to map your data to Darwin Core data standards, and
I wonder, have you looked into Darwin Core data package?
Because it's clearly more data than can be accommodated by Darwin Core archive.
But I wonder if you looked into data package, and if so, have you identified any
gaps, something that is in your data but still cannot be expressed in data package,
or is it enough for your needs? Did you look into it?
Thanks.
Yeah, more or less
it's enough for
us.
Probably, the missing part is related to the
facilities, because in our case, we
have the strong relation
through the data to the site, and
this part is probably
missing. That's all.
Thank you very much.
I was just wondering, because I see you created an
endpoint where you basically alias Darwin Core
terms to your own namespace.
No, we
created a vocabulary for our terms,
like Darwin Core.
And we use the same approach in order to
list
terms of our vocabulary to describe the data,
and we realize the
mapping for
align our vocabulary of terms to the Darwin Core.
That's the object.
I have a question regarding that. So you mentioned that you have this Darwin Core
match there. Is that for all of the terms you have there, or are there
terms which don't have that, and how are you modulating that since it's not shown
on the slide?
Not all the terms are matching.
And yeah,
in this example, we
present
matching
terms. But for more of these,
I don't know. I don't remember, but for
a lot, there is not a match for Darwin Core.
Thank you so much.
Again.
That
was good. Next up
is Cristina.
Yes.
Yes. Yours is...
Well,
I'll get it. Hold on. Watch this.
But it's right here.
Thank you.
Yes. All right.
I got it. I'm on the ball. All right.
Here we go. This it?
Yes.
Okay. Control L.
No.
Now. I don't need to give commentary while I'm doing this, right? Here we go.
All right.
Perfect.
Thank you very much. Yes.
Hello, everyone. I am Cristina, and I work
for the National Research Council of Italy,
but also in tight collaboration and connection with the LifeWatch research
infrastructure. And today, I'm going to present some of the services that we
provide to support semantic interoperability in the field of ecology
and also in environmental sciences more in general.
So
just to make sure that we all understand what I'm going to say in the next
slides, I'm going to refer to semantic artifacts
for ontologies, thesauri, glossaries, and controlled
vocabularies in general, expressed in model languages such as
SKOS, OWL, RDF schemas.
These resources are fundamental to ensure semantic interoperability of
data.
But also, we need semantic artifact catalogs because they provide
access to these resources. And today, I'm going to
provide an overview of EcoPortal, which is just one example
of a catalog of semantic artifacts that we manage internally.
And EcoPortal, of course, focus on the domain of ecology,
so all the resources included therein focuses on ecology.
So EcoPortal, of course, provide access, browse, and search capabilities
of semantic artifacts and of their terms.
But it also integrate VocBench, which is a collaborative editing tool
that we use to create novel resources based
on community needs. And we therefore manage
semantic artifacts across their all life cycles.
And
now, I don't have time to go too deep in this life
cycle, but if you are interested in knowing more, you can go and listen
to
my colleague presentation, which is going to run on Thursday.
She's going to present a trait thesaurus that we developed with our
community to standardize terms
about traits.
And then again, coming back to EcoPortal, it also provide a
FAIR assessment tool, which
can be used to infer
the fairness of semantic artifacts, but also an
annotator and a recommender to extract controlled
terms from natural text.
Now, EcoPortal is part of the OntoPortal alliance,
which is a consortium of different catalogs of semantic artifacts
for different disciplines and scientific domains.
And they are all based on the same OntoPortal technology.
So they more or less share the same features.
EcoPortal is also part of the federation, so a subset of this
catalog, those four catalogs in particular,
generated federated services for
search and browse, and they are also working on
releasing federated API. Which means that by accessing
one of these four catalogs, you can actually run federated searches
and query those four catalogs together,
which facilitates the
findability of resources that user needs
for a different task.
So now,
the situation, the landscape overall, it's much more complicated
than that because there are many catalogs of semantic
artifacts.
So
as much as
it occurs for data,
researchers need to
access different services to find the resources they need.
There are different type of semantic artifact catalogs, domain-specific
or generalist, and they are based on different technologies and different
standards to describe their resources.
The situation gets a lot more complicated, again, because
there are multiple access point, as I said, but also
many redundancies exist because there are many, many controlled vocabularies,
and sometimes they
describe the same entities,
and sometimes they're not mapped, so they're not aligned one another,
generating interoperability issues.
Sometimes the same resources are also available
on different catalogs, but with different versions.
And we also assess that
although these resources are fundamental
for the fairness,
sometimes they're not fair themselves because, for example, they lack of
key metadata description. And they are also, unfortunately,
underused for metadata annotation, so of course,
generating a lack of
semantic interoperability across data and across
catalogs.
So for this,
in the attempt to mitigate some of this challenge,
we
took the opportunity by collaborating with the other research
infrastructure
to generate another service that could
query all the existing-- well,
28 existing catalogs of semantic artifacts
from one single access point.
So basically, from the terminology service, you
can run federated searches on 28 different
catalogs,
and we therefore built 20 different connectors.
And the discrepancy in number between connectors and
catalogs is due to the fact that
the catalogs based on the same technologies need just one
connector that can be configured using different parameters,
but basically, the connector is the same.
These connectors can offer also discovery capability to user.
So if a new semantic artifact is available in the source
catalog, the users can be
alert.
But also version monitoring capability, so the system can be always
up to date with the new
releases and updates of any ontology or
thesaurus available in the source catalog.
Then, the service also offer search
and annotation capabilities, and
these services are actually available as widgets that can
be embedded into external application.
We tested this widget in three different metadata management
systems, and
these widgets are also available and accessible from the main
website,
just for user to test their functionalities.
So if they are interested, then
we can work together to integrate these services into their
system.
Finally,
we also work together with other research infrastructure
and semantic artifacts management to
align resources. So to create and build novel
mappings in between resources that are used by
these communities.
We build over 3,000
novel alignments
across six different semantic artifacts by
using semi-automated tools which are included in
the terminology service.
Then
of course, we want to continue
our activities, especially for the alignments.
We want to involve the community, but we also want to
test other
services. For example, other alignment tools, because
our tools at the moment are efficient, but also the
process is still very time-consuming, so we want
to
announce the available services.
But of course, we need to engage with the community to
test our services and provide feedback to us.
But also promote the reuse of what we developed because
these services are actually
based on open-source software, so they can be reused and
reapplied to other domains
beyond environmental sciences. And
thank you for the attention.
Any questions?
Yes.
Thank you for the presentation. I have a pretty naive question,
basically. You mentioned at the beginning all those portals, EcoPortal,
AgriPortal, BioPortal, BiodivPortal, et cetera, and
OLS and so on. And all of these portals provide ways to host
ontologies, to have
SKOS thesauri, and to
promote, to publish alignments between all of those and so on.
So
my very naive first approach would be, okay, do
we really need something on top of all of this to federate them and query
all of them? Or shouldn't we have services that allow
to say, "Okay, I'm using
EcoPortal.
If there is something that's not in there, I will develop a service that will
replicate that from another portal, import it
into the portal I need, instead of having something on top of it that's going to
do the federation."
Why don't we have several times the same vocabularies
hosted in the same portals, which is basically already the case.
Lots of ontologies are replicated, so why not continue this way?
Well, yes, as you said, this is the situation at the moment.
But the fact is that, first of all, it creates a management
issue. As I said,
different resources are available across different services, but then
they are not aligned one another. So they have different versions,
different metadata descriptions, and it's
difficult for a user to understand
which is the most updated version,
which is the canonical repository I have to look into.
So this is one of the reason. And then also,
sometimes we do not work
just in a specific field. We
manage multidisciplinary data, so we need access to
different
repositories or catalogs. And instead of looking into one
of them each time, it could be
more efficient to just have one access point.
This is one, well, the reasons.
Any more questions?
If not, then we move on to the next talk.
Do we have two minutes? We're having some technical difficulties.
For some reason, this session's not being viewable through Whova.
We're not sure why. But there is a Vimeo link, which is now in the chat.
So,
sound good? I think we'll figure it out. All right.
So
next up. How's it going?
Let's see.
So as you put the Vimeo, yeah, the Vimeo link's in the chat, so if you're talking
to people, you can take out the-- In the link there. All right.
Let's see.
Yeah, that's Vogt. Perfect. Oh, no, I have yours. No, you know what?
I have yours right
here. Thank you, Lars. Perfect.
Thank you.
Sure.
So hello, my name is Lars Vogt. I'm, since January this
year, in the Leibniz Institute for the Analysis of Biodiversity
Change. I'm very happy about that, because the last seven
years, I was more in the field of engineering and material
science.
And,
well, let me see how this works.
So,
the abstract that we submitted was basically an earlier
version of a framework that we have
substantially revised since then.
And so now I would present the updated content
with a new title, "The Triple A Principle."
And we want to be transparent about that.
It's a purely conceptual framework for now, with no
implementation yet.
So what's the problem space that we address?
We would love to have a system where restoration practitioners
could ask questions about what to do with, for
instance, their degraded mangrove site,
so that they can build an intact mangrove site again,
thereby taking into account the very specific context of
that site. And then the system would give back which
actions should theoretically be appropriate,
but also then from these, which are applicable to that
specific context, giving also some
documentation of the cases where that was successful and
where that failed.
So what
would such a system need in terms of knowledge representation
to support actionable knowledge?
And the typical answer you get is usually, it should be fair, of
course. Data and metadata should be fair, and knowledge should be machine
actionable.
But if we look into that, we all know what fairness means.
We know how to achieve fairness.
But we also know that fairness is not a Boolean property.
It's basically describing a continuum.
And what you often see is people say, "I made my data
fair," but what they did is they made the metadata of their
dataset fair. So they produce fair containers,
but not necessarily fair content.
And we believe for many to make
knowledge actionable, we have to provide fair content.
So that's the first part. The second, machine
actionability. Well, if we look at that,
machine actionability usually means we take information in,
and a machine transforms it and produces
some data, information out. That's a data
transformation process. And often machine actionability
means allowing data transformation, supporting data
transformation operations.
But when we talk about actionable knowledge,
we also refer to human actionability, and that
includes different types of processes, operations, not
only transformation operations.
So for instance, humans
have to interact with the world. So they have an
object given, and they want to designate it to a term.
Or they have a situation given, and they want to describe it and
produce language,
data, representations. That's an epistemic operation.
And of course, that works the other way around as well.
We have a term given, and we want to identify, recognize the object.
And the same with statements. So we have these epistemic
operations,
and of course, we have intervention operations, where we have
material entity going in, and a transformed material entity going
out. And in between, we have that intervention
process.
And I will focus on that type of operation from now on.
And consequently, neither fairness nor
machine actionability are sufficient criteria for actionable
knowledge for such intervention operations.
So we're dealing with a knowledge action gap,
and of course, there are many reasons for that, and
part of that is representational, and that's where I will focus on.
And there are three challenges.
The first challenge, it's actionability.
What practical knowledge is required to achieve a given goal?
And if we look at our intervention operation-- Oh,
sorry.
So we see
to be successful
What knowledge do we need? The case of a degraded
mangrove site turning into an intact one.
We need procedural knowledge, exactly descriptions,
directives, what to do step by step towards a
specific goal.
That's
actionability. That's required to be actionable.
And current FAIR infrastructures typically
address or represent what is the case, but do not
provide the procedural knowledge required to intervene
and transform a given situation into a desired situation.
The next challenge is applicability.
Does that knowledge hold here?
So looking at the same example, we see, well,
we can plant propagules,
but we know that this would not always result in an intact
mangrove site. So we know that actionability
doesn't equal applicability because of context dependencies.
So we have to provide applicability conditions.
So under certain conditions,
we know this might work, and then you can
basically
compare your contextual information with the applicability
conditions, whether it meets or not.
This is all just from the representational side.
The third challenge is auditability.
So how do we know it works and where has it
worked and where has it failed?
So in addition to the applicability conditions, we want to
have a feedback loop where we get applicability reports
back
that can help us to refine these applicability conditions.
That's auditability.
So in our example, the mangrove site salinity may
have fallen outside of the documented success range,
and if we would have known that before,
we could have chosen a different
approach to reach our goal.
So these three As, they form
what we call the triple A principle
of actionability, applicability, and auditability, which are,
we think--
first of all, they're nested and there's an order, so applicability
presupposes actionability, and auditability
presupposes applicability.
And we think that these are sufficient and necessary
criteria for
the representational side of actionable knowledge, and you can read more
about that in our paper, which is available on Archive.
It's a preprint.
So how can we represent that?
One possibility to represent that is using what we
call the semantic units framework,
and it's a very basic idea. In this case,
statements are first-class typed units so that you
can address them
and refer to them within a knowledge graph.
And the general idea is really you have some semantic content, and
it's really not important how it has been modeled, but
you have an identifier that represents this content and that is
classified.
That's the main idea of the semantic units
framework, and now you can refer to the content here.
And if you want to hear more about the semantic units framework, there are two
other talks that refer to that.
So based on that, we can build an action unit where
we have all the components linked
to other part
that are necessary for actionable knowledge.
So we have the input specification, the output specification, a
plan specification, and an objective unit for a
specific objective.
So that's
what we need for actionability, and then there are further components if we
want to also
meet the applicability and auditability.
So we add the applicability conditions unit
to that for an applicable action unit,
and the empirical evidence unit for an audited
applicable action unit.
So you see we have these three categories.
That's the most inclusive one, action units, and then
subclass is this, and subclass of that is that.
And then we can go even further, also supported by the
semantic units framework. We can have conditional action units.
So we can basically define an if clause that is a
question unit. It's like a query that we could
also execute within the graph. And if we have a hit,
then the then clause applies, which is a directive
unit. It says what to do,
and this could either be something that triggers a
process within the graph to add some
transformed data,
or with a proper tooling around it, it could
also trigger a machine to do something, external agent, or
tell humans what to do.
And with that, we have a graph-native decision logic
that we could basically build around the graph
so that the graph becomes a context-sensitive decision
support system and not a passive store
So to sum it up,
if we apply these three
principles or criteria of the Triple A principle
to knowledge engineering, we can
build
knowledge graphs that support actionable knowledge.
But as I said, that solves only the
representational part of the problem.
And there are many more things that the paper addresses.
I'm not going into details here because of time, but
you're very welcome to read it and I would love to hear feedback
on that as well.
And that's it. Thank you.
We have time for questions?
Plenty of time, 12 minutes.
Fantastic. We have 12 minutes for questions, so
fire away.
Hi. Thank you. So that's a very interesting approach, but if I understand
correctly, that would require to have all the human knowledge
about ecosystem restoration put in standardized terms, and that's a
very ambitious goal. So my question is, do you have any thoughts on
what would be the first step to practically achieve this situation?
How would you approach that? Thanks.
I'm lucky I have three talks here, and in the third one we address
exactly that. So I know that it's a real-- I call
it the semantic parsing burden. If you have to formally
model in formal semantics content, it's
really hard, often. I know that because I do that all the
time, and especially procedural knowledge is really
hard. But I think there are ways where we can basically
use natural language and do with
vector embeddings,
make it findable, and integrate it into the graph, and
I will talk about that on Friday.
Any more questions?
James.
She asked one.
All right. Fantastic. Thank you, sir. All right, great.
So for our final talk
of the session, let's get there. Let's see.
I start these up early. It's weird.
I do like when my inner dialogue is broadcast over a microphone. It's pretty good.
All right.
Let's see.
Ah, here we go. All right. We got it. All right.
Oh, it's recording. Oh, fantastic. Okay.
Hello, everybody.
All right.
Good. You got it? Okay, great. All right, let's do it. All right.
Hello, everybody.
My name is Dima Mazarin, and I want to
share our experience with a new data
format that we currently use in Species File
Group.
We have massive biodiversity data that we
work with.
That is four billion years of evolution,
and
there are more than two million described species,
and for all these names, there is information in
publications, in distribution,
genetics,
audio,
images, video files, taxonomy, and so on.
This is massive amount of information, and we
want to
exchange this information with others, as well as do other things.
And let's look how we do it now.
For example, we can take Darwin Core archive file and
send it to our friend, to our colleague, or to some
organization.
We can do the same with the Catalogue of Life data package or
with Darwin Core data package.
And all of them are text files.
It is just normal text files in JSON, XML, and so on.
And this approach works quite well.
One problem, though, these files are inert.
To be able to use it, we need to import the data into
database,
and we are not having this skill to do
that
all the time.
So we thought what will happen if we
access
exchange format directly?
What will happen?
Let's take in as an example MP3
format for
audio files.
We don't need to convert it to anything.
We
take it from somewhere, put it on our computer or on
our phone,
and we can directly play it immediately.
We don't need conversion.
We can send this file to our friend, and
our friend can use it directly. We can convert it from
one format to another.
We can create music, and save it as a MP3
file.
We can aggregate them into
our music library, or
something like Spotify can use this format
to stream music to us.
And now let's look what we have. We developed
SF Borg project, Species File Borg project.
It uses active
SFGA format. Why it is active? It
means we do not need to take the file in
SFGA format and then convert it somehow,
put it in a database. We can use it directly
by
pointing some other application to this
file, and it will immediately be useful for us.
We do not need to learn anything about the
SFGA internal format for that.
So what can we do?
We can exchange these files, of course.
We can collect data and put it into
SFGA format. For example, with the taxonomic editor.
We can aggregate several of them into a database.
Let's say this is what we do with GN Verifier.
We can preserve these files.
We can analyze them.
We can go inside of these files and learn
what is inside with
ease.
We can disseminate data that is in SFGA
formats.
So how does it work?
SF Borg is based on SQLite database.
It is a very unique database.
It has a single file, so it is very easy to
send it from one person to another.
Database is very fast and very scalable.
It can work with terabytes of data.
It uses standard SQL,
so it is very easy to query it.
The format of SQLite was stable for 30 years,
and it is supported at least until 2050.
Files that we send can either be as a text,
if we
create a SQL dump from the database, or we can send
database directly in a binary format.
It is pretty much guaranteed to work on another person
computer.
SFGA is evolving SQLite schema,
and the schema is the standard that we use.
SQLite files are highly compressible,
and this format is so good that Library of Congress
uses it as their archival format together with
XML and JSON.
At Species File Group, we use SF Borg in
production.
We convert harvesting, we harvest
data from
other sites, and we put it into SFGA format.
We convert, for example, Darwin Core to Code
DP and
backwards.
We validate data, and we aggregate data
from several SFGA files.
So what is at the core of SF Borg? Of course, the most
important thing is the standard itself.
We call it Species File Group Archive format.
It is a SQLite database schema,
and it uses semantic versioning.
So, for example, when we reach version one, we
guarantee that this format will be backward
compatible for a long time.
We also have a Species File Library.
This library
has a shared functionality
that many applications can use
and reuse this library.
Then we have application, it is called SF,
and this is our conversion tool. It allows to
convert, for example, CSV file into Darwin Core.
It can take Code DP file and convert it into
global names.
And it is done through
SFGA as an intermediary.
We have Harvester, and Harvester allows us to convert
to SFGA
idiosyncratic datasets, datasets that
are not following standards.
We have a project called GNDB. It is an application
that allows anybody, including us,
to
take SFGA files and assemble from them
a database for name reconciliation and resolution.
I'm going to talk about this on Thursday.
And we have project, which is most recent one.
It's called Hive.
And Hive is a taxonomic viewer,
editor, and validator.
So what else can we do? For example, we can
take SFGA file
and write an application
that will create a website from the data in
this file.
Imagine that
you are some kind of a
taxonomist. You have data. You convert this
data using SF
into SFGA, and
you immediately have a website with all
information in your data available for everybody.
We can write an application for curation of the
data using DIF that we already
have. Or, for example, we can make artificial
intelligent interface to
datasets in SFGA format.
I would imagine that it is possible to have
hundreds of instant access applications
for any biodiversity dataset in SFGA format
with zero additional work from the user.
And this is the end of my talk. Thank you so much for listening.
Fantastic. Do we have any questions?
I think
he's online.
Hello, everybody.
There we go.
All right.
I think he's online.
Maybe he is. Do you have the chat?
No, he's not.
He's what?
He says still working
in the chat.
Oh, yeah.
Zoom chat.
Oh, yeah, that's right. Okay. Zoom chat.
Is he in? I only see one participant view.
Yeah.
Everybody good? All right. We'll end with this. Here's a trivia question.
How many terms are in Simple Darwin Core? Who knows?
I know.
Two million.
Higher.
Anybody else? 205. And how many will be in there after mineralogy
extension goes through?
250-something.
It's a lot of terms. So that's it, guys. Good. Thank you for coming today.
I appreciate it.
Well done, right?
All right.
Cool.
Session now. And hello everyone. Welcome
to LT Lightning Talk 16,
Community Power Research Ready Citizen Science for
a
Digital Future. Just read it out, make sure you
come into the right room. Okay. And
I'm Melissa Liu from GBIF Edge Regional Support
Team and GBIF Knowledge Taiwan. And
I'm the moderator here, and there are two organizers
attended virtually, and they are Vijay
and Ram. They all get involved in citizen science
for decades in India.
So,
okay. And before we start the session, let me
introduce about the rules later. So we will
have six presenters later, and each presenter
will have about six minutes for presentations.
And when it's time to, two minutes,
right? Yeah. Two minutes to go, please check Tim
here, the volunteer here, to see the
time reminder, and then where another one minute to go.
Yeah.
Oh, sorry, two minutes, and time's up. Okay.
There are two reminders for that.
Okay. And after each presentation, we can
have about two to three questions for each
presenter. So I'll ask you if you have any questions.
And then, okay.
And then before
I introduce the first presenter,
I have just some opening remarks from the
organizers. So I'll just read them out to introduce
about this session. So,
okay. So what they say is, "Welcome to today's
sessions on bringing together local community volunteers
and the digital tools that power modern nature
conservation. As citizen
science moves toward automated and
robot-ready data systems,
our big challenge is keeping the human, local,
and all-inclusive spirit that makes this work
so special. So over the next hour,
we'll hear from my speakers on how to design
better programs, support our volunteers, and
turn community observations into powerful research
tools. So together, we hope to build a
future where people and technology work side by side
to protect our planet's biodiversity." Okay.
So
let's start with the first presenter, is the
Ashwin A. from India,
and he's
already prepared for the recording.
So just let me
play it.
Okay.
Hello, everyone. I'm Ashwin. I'm here to present an interesting insight
into citizen science. So I'm going to capitalize the invisible ledger.
That is, we'll check into the cost of production, shadow pricing methodology
for valuing the open source biodiversity assets in India, presenting you
with Lavanya Patil and Adarsh Pradhan.
So in India, we have almost 2.8 million citizen science
observations, and they're all open access and the market price, rupee zero.
But that doesn't mean there is zero production cost, right?
We have the field effort, taxonomy expertise, personal capital, digital
infrastructure.
So all the production inputs remain invisible, but they are very under-recognized
in the economic contribution. So the real question is, what does it actually
cost to produce a reusable biodiversity occurrence record?
So we did an analysis.
So the person goes into the field, they observe, they document, they identify, then
they submit into a digital platform, which then goes into DBIF, and then it
is reused for research, AI, SCI, et cetera.
This has been applied for different policies at an international and national
levels.
So what you're looking at as an economic asset is a reusable biodiversity
occurrence record that is well-documented, identified, and structured,
standardized, and interoperable.
This is not the same as just taking a photograph or about taking a voucher
specimen. Both of them are different, and they have their different values.
So this is technically the build of cost of building one
biodiversity record. So we divide into three, core production, data infrastructure,
and participant capital. So for core production, we saw that for
the field efforts, all of them are taken for low to
mid and high range. And then we made into
average value. For field effort, we saw almost ₹104 per hour.
For taxonomy expertise, ₹133 per an hour.
For platform infrastructure, it's ₹3 to ₹15 per record.
So the bare minimum replacement cost is almost ₹85 to ₹516 per
record. For data infrastructure, it's a little high, just ₹2 to ₹5
per record extra. That is ₹87 to ₹521 per record.
And then for participant capital, we did three different participant mix.
That is for dedicated hobbyists and opportunistic.
So for them, we did a weighted participant component for the equipment
depreciation as well as their other expenditures.
It's almost ₹80 to ₹160 a record. So in total, we have ₹137 to
₹676 as an estimated production cost per
occurrence record.
But if you are comparing it with the professional data production cost, that is a
professional, let's say a private or an NGO who does this,
they cost almost ₹700 to ₹3,500 to
produce a data point. Again, this records everything, changes,
varies from project to project and work to work, but this is the general trend.
As well as an institutional service like the government, they put in almost
₹2,500 to ₹7,000 into
every specimen output they do.
So this comparator is not actually equivalent.
So
their data quality is actually pretty high because they have a lot of stuff
ongoing, like let's say curation, reference, forensic scientific functions, et
cetera. This comparison actually estimates the expenditure associated with
producing comparable biodiversity occurrence information, not the replacement of
a physical specimen. So each of them has their own differences.
So now why does this zero rupees matter?
Because even the market price is zero, there is an invisible input that has been
going into it. That is their labor, expertise, capital, infrastructure, et cetera.
They're all under-recognized. Production value is not at all observed, and it is a
technically an under-investment.
That is spatial gaps, taxonomic biases, validation backlogs, et cetera.
So the citizen science does not eliminate the production cost, but it
redistributes it across citizens, experts, and digital
infrastructure.
So now what? So the citizen observation to natural data infrastructure, this
is how we can go by. So in India, we have 2.8 million observations, and if
we put an illustrative baseline value of ₹100 per record, you can see that
there's almost 48 crore rupees indicated production ledger
that's out there. So we have to recognize that citizen science is a
productive data infrastructure.
Then we have to put efforts into standardizing it, and then we actually have to
co-invest into platform validation coverage capacity so that the future valuation
extensions can be used, like your TEE frameworks, your physical
multipliers, your downstream policy returns, et cetera, all has to
be
extended through it. So the open access actually removes the price of access
and not the cost of production. So with this, I hope I was
able to give a new insight into this part of citizen science.
So thank you. To connect with us for any inquiry, please scan and
let us know. Thank you.
Hello, everyone. I'm Ashwin. I'm here to-
Thank you. Okay. I'm not sure if Ashwin is online now, but
if you have questions for him, you can type in on
the Whova app. And actually, he has two
presentations, so you will see his video again later.
So you can maybe keep your questions till the last,
and ask him
at once. Okay. So let's move on
to the next presentation.
Okay. Yeah. It's Alessandro Olgiati from
Italy.
Yeah. Thank you.
Thank you.
Thank you. Yeah. My name is Alessandro.
I'm from Italy, from
CNR, National Research Council in Italy.
And
I wanted to present... Thank you. Yeah
Here, I wanted to present
an example of how to
elevating a community observation into research
data. And our vision at the moment is,
rather than forcing a citizen to produce
structured data,
this one,
we build a workflow,
R package, to elevate this observation in
a community data structure
assigned.
We use
iNaturalist as a base of
observation, and we are treating iNaturalist
as a service. And we have a
case study using ELTERA European
Research Infrastructure. And
if you don't know, this European infrastructure
is a distributed pan-European research infrastructure,
and the mission is to study long-term
and
multi-decadal
scale
ecological variation and parameter.
And
already
mentioned,
we produce
R package,
the link is
there, that download the
observation from
iNaturalist
using the boundaries of ELTERA
RI site.
We automated the semantic enrichment
using alternative
sources like UCN, EUNIS is in
database, and also the information necessary for
our infrastructure. And
the output is a research-ready
interactive map, analytical chart, and table.
And
we have used four pillars for
enrich. One is about UCN
Red List,
the
EU Habitat and Bird Directive, and nativeness
using ESIN database and, again, standard
observation. And we obtain a table and a map
with this information of all the observation from
iNaturalist with all information mentioned
in these four pillars.
What is the benefit? Is a dual benefit for
LTER-RI and for citizen science. For
ELTERA Research Infrastructure, research site,
we have a direct
contribution for
augmented the information and observation and
expanded spatial coverage of
this
observation. And from citizen,
we consider that
we have a co-design, enable a
volunteer to engage directly in campaign
and in future campaign for a European Research Infrastructure
and elevated scientific value
for observation. That's all for my time. Thank you.
Any questions?
It's okay.
Yeah. Any questions to
Alessandro?
Oh, not from... Okay.
Thank you so much.
Yeah, thank you. Thank you so much.
Okay. And the next is,
let's see.
Okay.
Ryan Martin and eDNA Explorer.
Thank you.
You can use this.
Thanks.
Hi, everyone. I'm Ryan. I'm here from eDNA Explorer, and I'm going to tell you
about some work we did with community organizations and their work in the LA
River restoration.
So to begin with, the LA River, it's in Los Angeles, California.
It runs from the San Fernando Valley through downtown LA, out to the
river in Long Beach. In the 1930s, there was a really severe flood that
happened, and in order to try to control flooding for the future, they started this
process of channelization along the river.
And today, about 95% of it is now channelized and encased in concrete,
which you can imagine affects the biodiversity in this area.
And so more recently, there's been a push now to remove that concrete and try to
revitalize the LA River.
So this work I'm talking about started in about 2019 with this Protect Our River
organization that brought together a bunch of community groups, land
managers, Indigenous groups along the riverbed, and it was all funded by Metabolic
Studio and CaliDNA at the University of California, Santa Cruz.
And they wanted to go about removing the concrete and seeing how that affected the
biodiversity along the Los Angeles River.
To do this, they turned to eDNA metabarcoding, which is a powerful tool to
monitor and measure biodiversity along here.
Just a brief intro, I'm sure everybody already knows, organisms can shed their DNA
into their surroundings. We can collect it, identify the sequences, and just get
a snapshot, little historical view of what species have been in that area.
For example, like this Muscovy duck
And so where eDNA Explorer comes in-- so for this effort, they
sampled 12 sites along the LA River over seven months and
using six different markers, so really got a snapshot across the tree of life here.
And our platform then is able to take all this data after they've collected it.
We do the sequencing, take care of all the FASTQ controlled
processing, all the taxonomic assignments, all the confidence around those, and
making sure it's as strong as we can, as well as building some community ecology
and machine learning models with this data.
So now I'm going to go over a little overview of what our platform enabled them to
look at,
without having to get into the nitty-gritty of the bioinformatics on their side.
So of course, we can see across the markers they looked at, the various species
that were identified. We incorporate in GBIF data.
They can look at the local area, state level, or national level.
We are working also on having it be able to upload data to GBIF, which we started
recently.
We can also look more specifically at GBIF if you're interested in specific
organisms. For example, there's crawfish, which we identified in several
samples and was corroborated by GBIF in that area.
And as expected, eDNA also was able to identify some that weren't observed in
GBIF, such as this freshwater
jellyfish, which was in about a third of the samples.
This is a really small organism, really hard to see by visual methods.
But with eDNA, we were able to identify it across 12 sites across all sampling
periods, so highlighting the importance of using this in
conjunction with other methods to get more information about the biodiversity.
Can also do some simple longitudinal analysis since they were looking all across
these seven months. Here we can see a variety of organisms identified by the
CO1 marker.
In the summer months and the winter months.
On the top, you can see organisms that were more prevalent in the summer, less
prevalent in the winter, and on the bottom, the inverse, less
prevalent in the summer, more prevalent in the winter.
So again, allowing people to get this overview of their data without having to
know how to manipulate it themselves.
In terms of community modeling, as I mentioned, they were interested in how
concrete affected the biodiversity in
the LA River.
And so we can say that it was quite a strong predictor across
the majority of markers that we looked at.
How we got about this was the platform takes about 400
geospatial data points collected from Google Earth Engine.
This covers things like precipitation, climate, greenness,
human activity, pollutants in the area, as well as a few others,
and the variables that people collect.
So any custom data you want to import will also be included.
We then run a random forest model and help try to model the
beta diversity of this. So you can see here, this is a principal component analysis
of the 18S eukaryotic marker. We see these two communities of channelized
and natural communities as partially channelized, kind of diffusing
across, suggesting that concrete has some impact on the composition
at these areas.
So our platform really enabled these groups, without much of a basis in the actual
science, to really have access to this more advanced tooling and understand their
data.
It's now continually being used to monitor their restoration efforts.
It's also in talks to be used as a baseline pathogen measure for the
upcoming Los Angeles Olympics in 2028.
And also, the various indigenous groups are using it as supporting evidence for
their revitalization efforts as well.
So, as I mentioned, this project came about from funding from Metabolic Studio, and
it was actually the founding project for eDNA Explorer.
We created the company then to support more groups with the lessons we learned from
this work, and helped in projects that they had going forward.
And of course, I
want to thank all the people that actually collected the samples and the
organizations that were involved with this work. Thank you.
Any questions?
That microphone is not in use.
Oh, okay. Thank you. Sorry.
Yes, any questions?
Yes, Tim?
It's really cool. Did you involve the community in the collection of the
materials at all?
Yeah. So they were the ones that actually did the collection.
So we'll help people plan the projects, and we have kits that help them
collect it, but generally, they'll be the ones that do the actual sample collection
arms field.
Any other online or...
No, for you, but for other speakers.
Any other questions?
Okay.
I think we have-
This one.
Oh, okay.
I think we need to switch.
Let me check. Okay.
Oh, yeah.
So the organizer, BJ, asked, "Happy to learn you are sharing
data with GBIF.
Would like to learn your workflow."
So that is a very new project for us.
We were
able to start uploading last week, so the workflow is in progress for that.
Okay. I think we will have another time for the last
Q&A session because now we only have a
few presenters. Thank you, Ryan, and we just move to
the next one.
Sorry, I'm not sure if the order is...
Okay.
So next one should be Prana
from India. Thank you
Hello.
Good evening, everyone. So I'm from India,
from Climitra. So we are a geospatial intelligence
company which maps invasive species,
agroforestry residues, and also
maps in all the agroclimatic zone how invasive species
adapt. So one of our project is in
the Gujarat, which is one of the place in
Kutch. So
what we do is that we map invasive species in that
region.
In that layer, we found that it's very important to include the
local communities which are present in that region to collect the
data, and because they are the one who are suffering
from these invasive species, and they are sitting on
ecological wound. So it's very important to include in
the whole pipeline.
Yeah. So, before deep diving to
how our pipeline works, I like to put some light on the invasive
species which we are mapping is Prosopis
juliflora. And it's one of the top
10 invasive species
listed by IUCN. And it was introduced in
to hold back the deserts. Definitely it made that place greener, but
also it killed the native species at that place.
And it has covered more than 50% of that region.
The whole region is around 45
million hectares, and it has covered 1.1 million hectares
in that region. And the main problem is that it's
killing the groundwater and also raising the soil salinity.
So there's a government mandate also to remove this species, and
slowly and slowly this species is moving to across all
Pan India in all the 20 plus agroclimatic zone.
So, yeah. So it was planted in
1961, as I told, around 31,000 hectares, but now
it has spread to 1.1 million. The main problem
is that
the species is killing the native species, which is what I
mentioned, and it's very important to include the local
communities.
So this is one of the classifier map which we have
developed using our geo foundation models of that region.
And this region is, by the way, it's bigger than Sweden.
So,
yeah. So the green part which you are seeing is
the Prosopis infestation across that region, and others
are the deserts, mostly deserts. And it's affecting the
local communities.
I have just a small video to show
how it looks.
I guess it's visible to you guys.
So these all land used to be grasslands, and now it's covered with the
saline species, and we are trying to restore it and map it,
including the local communities.
You can see our excavators trying to clear it.
Yeah, I think this.
So why to include local communities?
So first,
they are the one who are facing this issue, so it's very important to
them to involve in clearing invasive species and replant the native
species. So our ground team works as an orchestrator,
and they include different communities, not only in data collection, but
also in the restoration part.
And this all sits on our satellite model, so it creates as a
baseline.
This is our team working with the ground communities
to understand and to tell them how to do the restoration.
So it sits on two things. First, we have our voice
agents involved, so mostly these people are illiterate.
So it's very important to
include a technology which is very much analog on the
front end, but very much digital on back end.
So we have voice agents in their own language which helps
them to collect the data. And also, we have simple local
language forms which helps to create the ground truths.
And these ground truths helps in creating the
biodiversity level datasets, which we are creating
on the geospatial maps.
So it works in three ways. First, we confirm with the satellite
data, and then it goes in a cyclic loop where the
false positives are removed. And then we
do the occurrence part where the hotspots are to identify
the spectral indices and also how to benchmark the whole
setup.
Yeah. So,
this is one of the ways how we collect data.
So this is done by our ground team and also the villagers.
So, we get the lat-long and where to do the
extraction, where it's present. And we are creating our own
datasets, which we are working with the Google team to include in
the Google Earth as a dataset.
Yeah, I think first is we create the rows
and every row is going into three zones.
First is how data is curated, then
it's refined, and then
it's checked by the satellite datasets.
And then there's a feedback loop, which our ground team uses to
verify and validate it.
So, you can see
how it works, how it's present, how dense it is,
and
we maintain a proper field sheet, which is creating the datasets.
So, we are including the communities as
primary data producers and benchmarking it using the
geospatial mapping. And yeah, I think
the time's up. So,
yeah. Thank you.
Thank you, Pranav. Any questions?
Yes.
I was wondering how do the-
Oh, mic.
Well.
Yes. Sorry. Mic.
Because we have online participants.
Yeah. Thank you. Very cool.
How do the locals
greet you when you come and ask?
Yeah. So initially it was-
Sorry.
Yeah.
Initially it was with a lot of friction, but
as a ground team, we involved local people.
So they were as the point of contact with the villages, and it helped
because we are creating livelihood in restoration.
So these local people are only a part of the restoration work, and they are
getting paid also. And there's a government mandate to remove these
species. Yeah.
Any other questions?
Okay.
Yeah. Thank you.
Thank you. Thank you, Pranav.
Okay, and then next
is
Ashwin again.
So he has another recording.
Hello, everyone. So today I'm with you to present
and to benchmark India's biodiversity citizen science status, bringing you a little
comparative insights from Asia Nature's Challenge that happened, along with
Lavanya Patan and Prithvi Sharma.
So
Asia Nature Challenge was basically a challenge on iNaturalist which aims
to bring in more observations from the continent of Asia, where we have less
representation of biodiversity over there.
So we decided to have this challenge as part of it so we can have more
datasets coming from it, and we can have a more accurate representation of
biodiversity over there. So this is from
2024 to 2025, two years' dataset were analyzed.
We have almost 190,000
observations that came through it.
So these observations
get supported on iNaturalist. Once it's done, it goes into identification stage,
and then it goes into a research study stage.
But the question here is that citizen science is creating observations at a
huge scale, but how efficiently are they becoming
research-ready down biodiversity records?
So once an observation
is getting identified, it goes into research, monitoring, conservation.
But where exactly is this pipeline slowing down?
So on field,
from observation to volume,
observation volume to research-ready is when someone goes into a field, they
observe something, they upload that media on iNaturalist.
Once it's on iNaturalist, you have a community of people who are experts in
it, and people come and verify that taxonomy.
And once it's
research grade, so research grade is basically the community-supported ID on
iNaturalist, which doesn't exactly mean it's error-free, but it's actually used as
a proxy for identification. That is, it can call it data-ready.
Right?
And then once it's done, it is then pushed into GBIF, where it is
standardized, and it is further used for research, monitoring, conservation
activities.
So now the thing is that there is huge volume, but
there is a gap between volume and usability.
There is this
identification bottleneck that is happening.
So where exactly is this problem, and what is the problem?
So Asia is observing together, but the identifications are kind of uneven.
So we have compared three, four major countries over there.
So you can see that India brings in almost 47,000 observations, but
the amount of research grade is just 40%.
But at the same time, the other countries and other regional competitors
have almost 60% to 79% of research grade observations.
So this
means that India has more observations, but it doesn't mean that we have
more research-ready
records. So this regional difference is being emerged
after this analysis. So this means
that having observation surplus doesn't mean that it's
research-ready. Hence, there is a huge identification deficit over there.
And we also checked into where exactly is this problem coming into.
So we saw that India's bottleneck is technically taxonomically
gradient as well.
So we saw that
if you are uploading any bird observations on mammals, we have high attainment when
people are coming in. Also identifying it easily,
more like an easy,
the chance of getting it research grade is higher.
But when it comes to lower groups, like let's say plants and fungi, their
numbers are very less. It's almost 4%, very low attainment.
So this identification bottleneck is not a uniform thing that's spread out.
It's actually taxonomically gradient, is also one of the findings that we saw.
So
this taxonomic gradient
looks something like this. So there's almost a difference of 22
times between the highest and the lowest.
And what shapes this difference? We can see that there's identified
capacity, like who are the people who are there to identify.
Is the taxon difficult to identify from photographs or not?
And even the evidence that is there or the
digital support that is there, is it even enough to
identify it? So this suggests there's a huge difference, and it's not just about
observation, but it is to match the identification capacity.
So here is some suggestion to
get this thing sorted. So this is a strategy that we're proposing.
So one should target the backlogs first, that is the lower Punjab plants that are
actually 76. And then once you prioritize the backlog, we can eventually
connect to build the networks where scientists can connect together and
help each other. Once we have enough connections, we can run a targeted
mobilization like an ideathon. And then with all this thing, we can augment and
use AI-assisted human-verified help so that we make it
better. So this is the identification flywheel.
So we have more observations, more identification, and then it becomes into more
accurate data. Once we have that, we get more training and reference data.
And once we have that, we have better identifications, and hence we have more
people doing observation. So it's like a circle.
So the next one that is not more data, it's about usable data.
Thank you.
Yes.
Okay. Thanks, Ashwath-
Hello, everyone
... for the two presentations here.
So
again, if you have the questions for him,
please
type in on Whova app, and I think he will reply to
you by text.
Okay. So the last one
is Markus Oppermann from Germany.
Thank you.
Thank you. Hello, everyone. Because it's the last talk, I can be a little bit
off-topic here.
As you see,
my topic is growing together. I will go back to the start of such
projects.
Where does the data come from? I was involved in a project that's called
Increase,
where we have a small part that's called the Citizen Science Experiment.
In this project, we're dealing with legumes, making legumes visible for the people,
and especially here, the common beans.
And in this case, we thought we'd create a small citizen science
project that brings these beans to the people at the
end. We started with an application, a small smartphone
application where the people can register, can sign a contract to deal with the
material correctly.
Then they get a small set of beans,
and they can grow that by their own, and hopefully, they give us some information,
like observations also with the app,
and some images from
the plants. And we are hopeful that they will start to
exchange the material between the peoples. Why do we that?
Of course, we want to raise the awareness for plant genetic resources.
If I ask here in the room, who knows what plant genetic resources in my
mind is? Not all the hands will go up. I think one or two.
My colleague, of course.
But that was the main goal of the project, to raise awareness for plant genetic
resources, to show the diversity.
All of you know the
beans in the supermarket,
but they're
much diverse than we know.
And we want to take the opportunity to gather the data
all over Europe. The science are
spread all over Europe, and so we spread a well-defined set of
material and this well-defined set of traits
to the people, and we get back more than 100,000 single observations for
phenotypic data. And last but not least, it
was a trial for decentralized conservation that's more or less an
alternative for the traditional gene banks, where
we give the material to the people, they exchange it, they preserve it, and we
hope for long-term, we establish a community that will
preserve the material
by its own. So we start in 2021, and you
see it grows immediately more than we thought it would grow.
Overall, we have 25,000 citizen scientists at the end that
are registered in the system and deals with us that are more or less
every country in the European Union.
And so we have really a good data set at the end for
this. How we reach our community, of course, I will not go to every point.
There's obviously
clear things.
We have some anomalies, I would say.
One thing was you will see social media and national Facebook groups.
That's quite old school.
It depends a little bit on the structure of the people who are involved in the
project. We have seen there are more the gardeners community, and
they are more the traditional way, go more the traditional way, and at the end,
we have the Facebook groups quite stable over the time, and it was national, and
that shows also you have to speak the language of the people.
We also communicate here in the countries in the languages of the
people. Also with our support team tries to communicate and to answer all the
questions in the native language of the people.
The second and interesting thing was with
going in the media. In Italy, we have seen
TV interviews and radio interviews works quite well. That was the hot topic.
Looking at Germany, then it was better to have a newspaper article.
That was the thing that we did not expect. That was side effect, quite interesting.
So at least
our insights from this project, obviously, the key is social media.
Especially in Europe, if you want to establish such a project,
you have to go to the social media and be active in this to get the
people. And then it might be a good idea to have a practical incentive, in
our case, the beans for the people to attract them to join the project.
And if you want to have a good data quality standard at the end or good
data quality,
design a good application, have a lot of tutorials down to the
details, and
explain everything how to check all the traits itself and
At the end, we were surprised of the success of our project.
We have to
have a kind of new strategy how to scale our designs.
It means we had to hire a lot of people who's sending the material,
but we also have, at the end, to restrict in the third round, the amount
of sendings to 5,000 because it goes over our
capacities. So we are overwhelmed of the success we had.
And with this, I give you a little bit time of one of my highlight of
the comments of
the feedbacks that we got from our users.
And for that, thanks to all the people who are
involved in that, and thank you for listening.
Is there any questions
to Markus?
Okay.
Hi.
Interesting topic. Very unfamiliar, so I would like to
hear a little bit more about what do
the participants actually do in this project.
You send the beans to them, and then? Yeah.
Maybe it wasn't really clear.
We send the beans to them.
They get the beans, a well-defined set of five beans, five crops,
from five varieties, and they grow these
beans in the garden, in the balconies, at school gardens, in the field.
And during the season, they get the possibility
to observe that. Within the apps, they can
go to the traits they have, flowering time, or make pictures of that.
We created a kind of
sheet that they can have well-defined images for that,
and send us the data back. And then the second part was that,
due to the ability to exchange material by themself
using the app,
where we have assigned DUIs to the material itself, we hope
that they establish a kind of
community that conserves this material.
The task of gene banks, like
where I come from,
it's misleading. We're collecting seeds.
We preserve seeds from different cultivated crops.
That was the idea, to have a different approach, that a
community conserves these
varieties and this diversity.
Any other questions?
Okay. Sorry, just a quick
question.
What are the most common
social media in your community use?
Might be efficient for citizen science thing.
I don't think I can answer this question, because we were very special.
As I said, we had a community of gardeners,
mostly the elder generations, and they stuck in Europe to Facebook.
It's really a
special thing for Europe, maybe, that they stuck to Facebook.
We have, of course, WhatsApp groups that also works
quite well, but especially national Facebook groups
was always a surprise for us. We started also with other formats, other
media,
but that was what works in our
project. Maybe that isn't a fact for other things.
If the community is more agile or more younger, they stuck to other media, I
think.
Thank you.
I'm just curious.
Okay. And any other questions, if you have questions
to other present speakers, I think it's also fine.
Okay.
If not, I think
thank you for all the presenters today.
And also, I forgot to
have a big thanks to our golden sponsor to make this meeting
happen. And okay. Thank you all for
coming.
I think all the session, and if you still have QA
questions, you can still type in on the WhatsApp. No.
Whova app. Sorry. Yeah, Whova app. Okay.
So, sorry, since the organizer are
attending online, let me have the quick selfie
photo together, and I'll show them, okay?
So, here. I hope the light is fine.
Oh, yeah. Okay.
Three, two, one.
Thanks for coming.